Okay. Good morning, everyone.
So welcome to the principal design for
trustworthy AI, workshop.
This is the principle design for
trustworthy AI. Interoperability, robustness,
and safety across modalities.
And, the organize one of the organizer,
Lily Wen, from UCSD,
along with other, seven organizers,
Nia Hung from Washington State
University, from Stony
Brook University, Jack
Skeo Skow from Princeton,
Francisco Cross from Aulte University,
Chan Tan Singh from Microsoft Research,
Sabana, Tripassi, Fintel,
Lan Yuan from IBM
Research.
So this workshop focus on develop
trustworthy AI systems by principle design.
Models that are interpretable, robust,
and aligned across the full life cycle.
From training and evaluation to inference
time behavior and deployment.
This workshop aimed to unify efforts
across modalities which
includes language, vision, audio,
and time series. And across
technical areas of trustworthiness,
spanning from interpretability, robustness,
uncertainty, and safety.
Are six major topics that's included in
this workshop, The first one
is the interpretable and trainable models.
This includes the concept bottlenecks
and moderate architectures,
mechanistic interpretability, and concept based
reasoning. Interpretability for
control and real time intervention.
The second topic of the workshop
includes inference time, safety, and monitoring.
So this includes reasoning trace, auditing
LMs in VRMs,
inference time safeguards and safety mechanisms.
Channel of thought consistency and hallucination
detection, as well as real
time monitoring and failure intervention
mechanisms. The
third topic includes multimodal
trust challenges. So this includes
grounding failures and cross model misalignment,
safety in vision language and deep vision
systems, cross model alignment
and robot and robust multimodal reasoning,
trust and uncertainty in video, audio,
and time series models.
There's another three topics covered
in this workshop, So this includes
the robustness and threat models.
Which includes adversarial attacks and
defense, as well as formal verification
which certify the robustness
of neural networks. Also
enclose the safety guarantees.
The fifth topic includes trust
evaluation and responsible deployment.
So this includes human AI trust
calibration, confidence estimation,
as well as safety alignment.
The sixth topic includes safe
and trustworthiness in ILM agent.
So this includes, safety and failures
in planning and action executions,
emergent behaviors, and multi agent interactions,
as well as, auditing and debugging our
agents in the
real world deployment.
So in this workshop, we have
received a total of third,
312 submissions
and, 143
papers are accepted.
With 20 papers being spotlight
and a 123 as poster
You can find the accepted paper
list on our workshop website.
And thanks for, thanks to the program
committees who make this
the whole review process possible.
So this includes a certain area
chairs. As well as a 138
reviewers for this workshop.
And today, we will have, we are
honored to have five stellar speakers
and leaders in trustworthy AI.
To give the keynote talks.
So, professor Yan Liu from
USC she will talk about
actionable interpretability.
And professor Mihala Vanderschar,
from University of Cambridge shall
talk about interpretability in time series.
Professor Violet Palm from,
UCLA shall talk
about OEM safety And
professor Hamed Hassani
from, University of Pennsylvania
will talk about robustness and safety.
Last but not least, professor Fernanda
Villagas from Harvard,
shall talk about user facing interpretability.
So this is a a overview of the
schedule of today's workshop.
We are currently out of opening remarks.
And then we'll have the spotlight talk
session. So if you're the morning
spotlight talk session presenters,
please come to our left
So then, later, when you see
your slides, you can come up and
give two minutes presentation.
And then followed by the spotlight talk session,
we will have the first keynote from
professor, Mihala Vandazar.
And then at ten to eleven,
will have a coffee break as well
as our first poster session.
So, if your post
if your poster is a spot like
poster, then you will use the wall behind
me. So you will, use this
tape to paste your poster,
after, Professor Mihala's talk.
So that you can put your poster,
and then remember to take off your
poster at the end of the coffee break.
So at 11AM.
And then, if your poster is just
a regular poster, then you will
use one of them. So just use one
of one of this because
we have limited strip. And then
you can use the three walls over there.
So, from eleven to twelve,
we will have two keynotes from Fernanda
and Hamed.
And I will have a lunch break at twelve
to 01:30. So
the afternoon spotlight talk, so the spotlight
talk session two, starts
shortly at 01:40. So,
again, if you're,
if you're talk if you're so please
come to the left, at 01:30.
To 01:35 so then we can
start, sharply
at 01:40 for the spotlight talk session.
And then at two to 02:30,
we will have the first
keynote from Violet, and then we will
have a short coffee break.
In between. And then we'll have the
last keynote at 3PM.
So the afternoon poster session,
poster session two, then
again, if you are a regular poster, so use
one of the strip and then
paste on the wall there. If you are
a spotlight poster, in the afternoon,
then you will paste your,
poster after Yan's, keynote.
So at 03:30.
Okay. So are there any questions so far before
we move to the spotlight talk session?
Okay. So now we have one more minute
to, to start a spotlight
talk session. If you are the morning
speaker, please make sure you're on the line
of the left So come to the line of
the left, and then we will use the
order your paper ID.
Yeah. The first poster is
the paper number two. You
are the presenter? Okay. Then you can come
and prepare.
Make sure make sure your presentation
follows to, two minutes and
I will, raise the time up
paper there.
Okay. Everyone. I'm presenting
on behalf of the authors who couldn't be here.
This work is about Laura and
what we should be aware of when we're using Laura.
So to motivate us, Laura is
of course everywhere. It's the go to method that
you probably use whenever you're fine tuning
a model. However, we
haven't studied very much spurious correlations
and the fact under explored in real
world data sets. Which are rarely clean.
So things like leftover markup, metadata,
templates can all actually end up
having correlations in the fine tune model.
That Laura can latch onto. This
leads to shortcut behavior that makes models
unreliable and
worse if used by malicious actor that can be
injected into the dataset.
And so that's what we study here in this work.
So to do this, the method proposed
is called Seamless Spurious Token
Injection. And the idea is
to have a controlled framework to inject
spurious correlations into the dataset.
An example is one that you see up here on
the top right. Which is injecting a little h
one tag for HTML.
And while this looks innocuous, if it's
correlated at all with the class label that you're trying
find tune your model on, the model ends up learning this
as a shortcut doesn't actually learn what
it is that you care about.
The core result, I'm gonna kinda highlight
four things. One is that a single spurious token
is actually enough to dominate the predictions of
the model and prevent it from learning the pattern that
you do care about. Two,
there's a kind of a non monotonic relationship
between the lower rank, so higher rank amplifiers.
Even with light corruptions.
So there's no single safe rank that you can
choose. And then third,
the effect persists across token types, position,
model size, or training duration.
Even a 24,000,000,000 parameter model is
vulnerable. So it doesn't just go
away with scale. And then fourth,
and maybe most alarmingly, the author said
grammar checkers paraphrases
cannot remove these spurious correlations if they're in the
dataset. So the bottom line is
lower efficiency comes with an understudied robustness
trade off, Spares correlations are
a core part of what we should be
thinking about when we're using LoRa. So be aware of that.
Is the spotlight paper number for
here?
Okay. If not, then we will skip this one.
And number six.
Good morning, everyone. I'm Ms. Yu Wang.
From the University of Hong Kong. And
today, I'm happy to introduce our work,
DRM scope, the
first SE based framework, for understanding
and the controlling diffusion language models.
Okay. The first slide shows spots
shows the background. We see Sparse
encoder have become a useful
tool for, large language model. Right?
And recently, diffusion language model have become,
increasingly powerful and
promising alternatively to IIM,
but the key problem is
we still not yet know
how the OIM represent
denotes and
and control language internally.
So we just focus on two things.
First, can I see based on DLM
between? If if so, what
are the differences between SAE based
on DLM and RLLM?
Second, what's the potential of
SAE for deficient language model? With
the above questions, we just
create two new method. First,
we design SAE training for different language
models. Second, we designed method
of SAE to feature steering in
different language model. The right
figure shows details. More details,
please refer to our paper. And finally,
after we, training and using
SAE model,
we get really interesting insights
First, as each trained on
deep division model are indeed useful
Second, inserting SAE into
different into DLM
can reduce mask token cross entropy
loss, while, inserting one
SAE into LAM
often increases the loss.
Third, SE enable effective
steering, compared
to, in LRM.
So in summary, we think our work
opens a new path
a new interpretable and controllable pass
for, transverse a diffusion diffusion
language model. That's all. Thank you.
I'm good. Sorry. Can you hear me well? Okay.
Well, first of all, thank you everyone for coming
so early in the morning. I'll try to be quick.
And hopefully everything, makes sense.
Okay. So I'll start with some
quick background. So you know, if you're not
aware, there's been a lot of past work that
has shown that post training quantization
can affect social bias in large language
models. And so explain
first, of course, I'm sure you know you all know what large
language models are. Post training quantitization
is when you compress large language model
weights so that they can be run on edge
consumer devices. I'll try not to explain
with social biases because there's too many ways you can explain
that, but as one quick example, you can see
here, if you feed in a bias prompt to an LLM,
that's let's say attacking the elderly,
an unbiased response would be to disagree
with this bias prompt but
certain cases when you compress these models,
can actually give you the unsafe response.
Okay? And so this
was prior studies, they focused primarily on
data set specific changes and oftentimes
the results don't really generalize. As
a result. And so oftentimes this leaves out
when and why this happens to begin with.
And so this is kinda what we explore in this paper.
And so at a glance, what we
do is we combine 13 data sets which cover
range of definitions of social bias, close ended,
open ended, implicit, explicit, and
so forth. We standardize response
extraction. This is similar to,
what LM eval does. We compute normalized
probabilities. For for closed ended
responses and for open ended, we do
a gray decoding. And then we standardize as well
evaluation. We do this pairwise permutation
test to identify significant changes.
But we also look at response level changes,
whether or not a response flips and we
also look at the uncertainty of the response when that when
that happens. Okay. And so like I
said, we look at response changes and 10 LMs due
to five post training quantization methods
that are very well known. Okay. And so we
have three main findings. The first is that uncertain
responses are more likely to change.
Show this in two ways. One, just observed
that responses that have higher pre quantization
uncertainty end up changing
their response after we do this quantization.
But we also show with simple preference optimization
we increase their uncertainty,
directly, then this directly leads to more,
response flipping after. We also
show that course metrics can hide changes in response
flipping So even for datasets where it
shows that there's no significant change in
in the metrics, we still show
that up to, like, 13% of responses still
change even in these, scenarios.
And then we show that these response flipping
scenarios, these can affect subgroups asymmetrically
you zoom in across well, if you look at
all models, first, let's say targeting all
male, male persons, You see that
1.6% of responses increase in
bias. When you zoom into a single model
across all five quantization
methods, you see 7%. And when you zoom in even
further, you can find one instance where
18.6% of responses were biased.
Okay. There's a lot more, interesting stuff to say
but you'd like to chat about it, we can chat about it later.
Thank you.
Is the spotlight paper, number
10 here?
Okay. So let's skip this.
What about 12? Yours. Okay.
Hey. Good morning, everyone.
So I will present this paper on how
to attack IIM just in a
black box way.
So the setting here is that you
can you only have access to the black
box model with the text output.
You can imagine you want to attack a cloud
model, but the cloud model can only
output the text So here, you don't
have access to another ARM
or maybe the access to the probability
of a token. And,
the best thing you can do here is
by a smart question.
Here, we show you can actually
ask a a good question
in a way that you always give the
LM two candidates. So
and this generic method can be
applied to adversary examples of injection
or gel break. For example,
here we have two dogs, and the the goal
is to one of the motor to misclass
this to be not a dog.
Then you can always give one input
but with the two different, random
random perturbation. And then
you ask the model to pick one which is more closer
which is closer to your attacker goal.
So for example, the adversary example
here, is, that you wanted the model
to pick one that is less than 90
dog. And for prompt injection or algebraic,
you can ask the model. You can give the same prompt
but with the two different, suffix.
And ask the model which one is easier to make
you send a email or maybe
reply how to be the bomb.
And we sure it can be applied
to different models. So at the beginning,
many models just
around 0%, ASR. But with
this method, you can actually get
a huge benefit from just asking to
asking a live question with the two candidates.
And then we find the interesting phenomena,
which what do we call the security paradox.
That means, so here we show
the example with
different larger different model size. So with
larger model, actually
more vulnerable to this type of attack.
And we find that so for
the feedback model, when you want to get the
direction from the model, if you ask a better
model like g p five, it
actually it can actually reason
a bit about the two candidates and actually give
you the correct choice
So this is a security paradox.
Cultivately, we find that more
capable motors are more vulnerable
to this attack. And it's
actually can make it work
even without any log probability or model
parameter So you just ask the model
by two lines of question. And then
you can get the optimization signal from the
outputs.
And if you are interested in this paper, we
have the QR code here. And
also the code for the paper,
you can try to run it.
Okay. That's all. Thanks.
Yeah. Good morning. I'm
Lucas, and I'm happy to present our paper
here on exec certification
of neural networks against label poisoning
And, label poisoning means that
the a certain fraction of your training labels
in your dataset are manipulated to
induce miss classification in your model,
And certification means that we want to prove
that the model is robust or not
to these kind of manipulations.
Where state of the art methods are so called partition
based ensembles which
work by partitioning the training data
into disjoint subsets and
then train separate base classifiers
neural networks usually, on,
these data set on these subsets and
then, do a majority vote. And this
allows one to derive a certificate
because only a fraction of the base classifiers
will be affected
the manipulated training labels. However,
these certificates are usually
usually assume that a base classifier can
be corrupted by a
single manipulated
training label and thus are quite
conservative and usually and
we can assume potentially quite
loose. So the research problem we
tackle in this work is we ask
the question if and how we
can utilize white box knowledge of base
classifiers to get
tighter and better informed certificates for
the ensemble. And to
tackle this question, there are, two main
challenges. First, there
are no real effective white box certificates
for neural networks we use them
as a base classifiers and
second, if we would have such white box,
certificates,
it is aggregating
them to derive an ensemble
level certificate is a complex combinatorial problem.
So in our work, we tackle these two challenges
but first, deriving such an ensemble
level certificate that utilizes white box information
of the base classifiers in and
runs in polynomial time, which we achieve
by insights into the combinatorial optimization
problem. And second, we derive
a certificate for
sufficiently wide as a white
box certificate for sufficiently wide neural networks.
That we use as base classifiers and is
also computable in polynomial time.
Which we achieved through some insights from
neural tension kernel theory.
And skipping, the result, skipping
the figure here, for time reasons,
we find that this significantly improves
our black box certificates and we
also challenge, this paradigm
of the state of the art certificates
that deeper partitioning leads to better robustness,
but we rather find that this is just an artifact
of the looseness of the certificates.
Thank you a lot.
It's the spotlight paper 16.
Is it yours? No?
Is the Spotlight, paper number
16 author here?
Okay. So then let's skip this.
18.
Good morning. My name is Erin. I'm
excited to be presenting our paper
investigating data interventions for subgroup fairness,
an ICU case study.
So machine learning for health care is
known to be particularly
susceptible to distribution shift
for the main reason that different hospitals see intrinsically
different patient populations such
that you blindly train on combinations
of multisource data, you're not really clear
on what the effects are and you kind of yield
pretty unpredictable outcomes.
What's less studied is the fairness
How can we make informed data decisions
to improve accuracy upon a target
subgroup? We find that this is
a harder problem than when looking at whole
hospital performance for the main
reason that your, metrics are now
disaggregated by your actual attribute of interest,
in our case, it's gonna be race.
In the figure here, we see an example of
where adding data will give you
really desirable improvements over your whole hospital
performance, but actually even greater
reductions to specific
the black subgroup. Which is pretty harmful.
In a more subtle case, we actually
see that data adding data seems to yield
less than a percentage point increase in
whole hospital accuracy but actually
about 3.6% increase in your black
subgroup. So we actually would wanna add this
particular data source to improve our target
subgroup. Assuming that your other subgroups
remain neutral or positive.
So what we do in this study is audit existing
data interventions at that are used
in the whole hospital case to see if they work
at the precision level for individual racial racial
subgroups. On the
EICU and Mimic datasets for a twenty
four hour ICU mortality prediction.
We find that data selection heuristics that are known
to work in those whole hospital cases
don't actually transfer into the subgroup case,
so things that we tried include data
balancing, including adding the source that
includes the most black patients
or even the highest ratio of black patients.
We also use distributional similarity scores
such as k l divergence, and then we also introduce
our own similarity score and neither of
those seem to correlate with your
improvement in target subgroup population. So those
are pretty counterintuitive results.
As these are pretty natural heuristics to use
in the source case.
Mathematically, we can bound the impact of data addition
without making assumptions about the model We can
see in the right subgroup that or in the right
figure, that that is upper bounded.
So that means that our key takeaway is
just that even the best data
strategy for data addition can only do so much
without ensuring that you're models are
well calibrated and well fit to the
data. Thank you.
Can you hear me? So good morning,
everyone. I'm Simone, and I'm presenting
this work this joint work with Sade and
Alexander on the test
and training undermines a FTG upgrades.
So let me start from this. So this is
the leaderboard of the OpenAI's parameters flow
challenge, which is a, challenge aiming
at training the best language model
under very tight compute and time constraints.
And if you look at the first three approaches,
leading this challenge, you can notice
that they all use this
test and train paradigm. So the high
level idea of this paradigm is that
rather than keeping the model fixed at deployment,
you just perform a few gradient updates using
the signal coming from the
prompting input. Order to specialize
the model on the problem
that that has been given. So, we
just ask what does it does it happen to
the safety alignment when we perform this
TTT steps. And how an adversary
can like, leverage these
gradient updates to a Jira broker
model. So, yeah,
we framed this, these answer using
three different RAT models. So we
start with the, adversary trying
to jailbreak a CFL
alarms. LLM, and,
can be done in three different ways. So
either just, optimize the
prompt in a fully self supervised way,
or, it can provide a handful
of harmful prompt
along with, the
starting of an affirmative answer.
Pairs, in order and then train of these
in order to transfer the behavior
of replying to prompt.
To the original one. And finally,
we have the generation phase where we just
optimize for the starting of an affirmative
response condition on the input prompt.
So once we have the adapted model in one
of these three ways, just fed in the original
query in and just,
rid off the, potential harmful
response from the model. So we test
these three settings across, seven different models.
And we observed that the attack assess rate
at 10 generation increases
from 4% without performing any
kind of TTT up to
95% in, under certain settings,
like, for example, the few shot case.
We also show that TTT
can compose this also with existing
adversarial prompts in to further increase the
success rate. Of the attack.
Yeah. Thanks everyone. If
you have more questions, more details,
feel free to stop by the poster.
Okay. So next, we will have our
keynote talk from professor
Mihala Vandashar. So we'll set up first
and then I will introduce her.
Okay. So professor Mihala Vandazar
is the drum, Humphrey plumber
professor of Machine
Learning, Artificial Intelligence and Medicine at
University of Cambridge. Where she
leads the Vanderscore Lab.
Mihala was elected as
IAAA Fellow in '29, '29,
2009, and she has received
numerous awards,
including the own prize on preventive medicine
from the University of Cambridge,
National Science Foundation Career Award,
three IBM faculty awards,
IBM Exploratory Stream Analytics Innovation
Awards, and Philip, Make
a Difference Awards. And several best
paper awards. So without further ado, let's
welcome professor Michala Thank you
very much for the kind introduction.
And thank you for the invitation to
talk here. I my plan
in this talk is
really to excite you about
trying to love time
series which I hope you already do because
the reality is that everything in the real world
not something toyish, but rather something
than affects the real world.
Is often a dynamical
system from which we sample time series
data. And what I
also want to hope to I achieve in
this talk is not only to do
predictions, but also to try
to understand what is happening such
that we can have more trustworthy system,
more robust systems,
and also really rely on what we have
found out.
So first, I'd like to give a
big acknowledgment to my absolutely
brilliant student, Shistov
Capcic, who finished his PhD
thesis and this is very much based on
his thesis work and I'm very
fortunate that he is staying for now with
me as a postdoc. So,
okay, everybody knows and
loves doing forecasting on the basis of time
series data, and I'm delighted that this
is the case.
And we are doing really quite well
increasingly in in doing time to
in doing time series prediction.
But if we are really interested to
use these time series models in
high stake environments,
whether it's in climate change to make intervention
whether it's in medicine, whether it's
in finance, this is simply not enough.
And it is not enough even
if you, like me, have pursued
interpretability, have pursued uncertainty
quantification for time series and so
on. So I'm going to
take you a little bit back in time and tell
you that I always was interested in
time series, and one of the things that were important
to me is to try to understand the predictions.
And early on, we had good interpretability
for static information, whether it's from
images, or from, tabular
static data. But we didn't
have methods for understanding post
hoc time series interpretability
And here are two papers from
our lab that were the world's first
papers to try to look at time series forecasting
first based on features,
DynaMask, because just applying your favorite,
let's say, sharp values over
time don't explain a time
series, So then a mask was the first
way to do this post hoc, and then
trying to combine both feature based and example
based explanation in simplex.
And for a while, I was satisfied.
Till I took this to real practitioners
in both medicine and finance,
and it appeared that this is just not enough.
Just post hoc interpretability and uncertainty
quantification is not enough.
What they really needed is the ability
to what's happening and project
into the future. So you really
need its interpretability by design.
Which for some time, till I met Krzyztov,
I didn't thought was really possible.
So let me try to explain why moving
towards this type of trans
So we may want to forecast a two more volume
of a particular patient given the
baseline covariates and drug dose.
And standard explainability techniques,
whether the ones that come from our lab for
time series or others,
are, able to answer things like how
important is a specific
covariate for the prediction. Or
if we do, like in simplex, like
we did example based explainability
for time series forecasting, as well as future
interpretability, you may have
to answer an even more complex question. How
similar is this instance to other
instances in the dataset? This patient, for
But really to understand the model
well and give confidence to
practitioners to use it, you
need to answer what if questions. What would happen
to the model's prediction? If a
specific covariate changes?
Something that I call how to be. How
should the covariates be modified to get
a different prediction? That's very important
for a patient. Because they may want
to know what they can change to change this prediction.
Or how still be this? What range
of the drug dose values keep the
prediction the same? So
what we need to understand is change
in the trajectory. This is
much more challenging than understanding change
in single label output. Which I see
still many people doing.
So what we really need to do is
to do something humans usually do,
which is understand trajectories
by referring to the
trends and properties rather than just looking
at values. For
instance, you'll see here a few examples. The GDP
has been steadily increasing for the last
ten years. So you see what I
call the trend, which is in this case increasing.
And a property for the last ten years.
Let me give you another example.
Tumor volume decreases
obtains a minimum after six months,
and then increases.
So the trend is decreases for some time
and then increases. And you
have a property minimum at
six months.
So that I clear two years ago,
together with Shishtov, and Tennyson,
we introduced, this
interpretability by design time series forecasting
model. So not post hoc interpretability,
but very interpretable by design.
And we were able
to really predict shapes of
trajectories. So the way we did
that was dividing
the trajectory like you see here
in smaller intervals where the trajectory
has a particular shape that we call motive.
Increasing and concave, decreasing and concave,
etcetera. And a sequence
of these motifs we call composition,
and this represents the general shape of
the trajectory, And more generally,
we can tell you where the transition
points are going to be.
Taking place. And
this is very important if we want to
truly predict but also
understand the trajectories.
And in time view, we came up with a
methodology to do
predictive modeling. So time series
forecasting that is interpretability
by design, not post hoc, but interpretable
by design. So we do prediction with these type of interpretable
models. And we are able to do them
with very high efficiency, actually.
But also visualization.
I will not go into a lot of the details
because I want to excite you about
the idea. Hopefully, you'll find it interesting and
take a look. And bring
to yet one step further.
But before I do that, I want to just focus
one more time on what times you can provide
and can do for people in their that may
be interested in safety, the trustworthiness,
and so on. So
one thing it can provide is what we call
bilevel transparency. So
we have, on one hand, trends,
and this tells you how the shape of the trajectory
will change. And when it will
change. Increase, decrease,
oscillating. Also properties
how the key features of the trajectories change.
When does it peak? When there is an asymptote?
When it's a minimum?
So in this way, with time view, you are
able do interpretability by understanding
global behavior, not only just individual
points, You can have true transparency.
You can do counterfactual reasoning.
And also you can debug and bias
detection. You can detect for instance,
a realistic trends, unrealistic
asymptotes, unrealistic peaks, and
so on. Which again is very important
for any real world application that involves
time series. In this
way, we are able to understand the trajectories
but not yet go to
the next level. So initially, we were
quite happy with this, and I still love
Time View. And I recommend it to all
of you who want to do real
world trustworthy
prediction and forecasting. But
what this doesn't provide us is a true
understanding of the underlying system.
And for that, you really need to understand
not only the trajectory but also
the characteristics of the underlying system
that produce this time series.
And this requires more. You
and the reason this requires more and we should
want more is because it can do
things prediction can't do.
For instance, we can, extrapolate
beyond observation data. We
can understand and forecast behavior
under unseen conditions,
something that may sound even strange to somebody
in machine learning, which just is used to
just learn from data. It
can tell us when the system will stabilize.
And for how long it may stabilize.
What will happen? Will that stability
still stay the same or change under this
distribution shift? And also,
if we know something about the system,
we can align them with what
we know about the system constraint.
So I want to take two examples to
show to you why I find this very important. So
we have data. For instance, we in
pharmacology, drug concentration effect
over time. And, of course,
we could do forecasting with could
predict the next measurement, which is as
we discussed, kind of boring.
Or I could predict, if you like, the trajectory
into the future. Using something
like time view. But even
that may not give us enough
information. Because while the model
prediction may remain accurate locally,
I do not know what will happen
under possible changes.
So for safe and transport use,
of such dynamical,
systems under intervention, and here the dynamical
system is an important one, is the human body.
We need reliable extrapolation
to new doses and time horizons.
Because in clinical trials, I
was not enrolled in this clinical trial.
So I'm a different system than the one that
was used for validation and safety
I need consistency across patients.
I need interpretability of behavior
onset peak decay. And
I also need alignment with what's
known about this dynamical system.
In this case, physiology, the human
body. So safety requires
capturing how the system behaves, not just fitting
observed data. The
same is true in finance. And
I can give you numerous other examples outside
finance. In finance, we often
observe price or returns over time, and we
may want to predict the next movement, and that's
really not enough. Because what
we need is robustness under regime
change. For instance, a
COVID outbreak or a war outbreak. Stability
under distribution shift. Interpretable
behavior, in terms
of trend, volatility, transitions,
when these transitions may happen,
and also reliable behavior under
stress condition. So again,
we need trustworthiness that is determined
outside the training distribution.
So for that, we really need to understand
the underlying dynamical not
just the the signal. And not even
just the signal under counterfactors,
also under all sorts of interventions.
How to do that? So
So we can learn dynamical systems from
data, and one way to do it is symbolic
regression. Or symbolic regression
type methods. And in our lab, we have been
quite obsessed and still are obsessed
with, building better and better
methods to disc discover
ODs and PDEs and SDs from data.
But the challenge with doing that
is that they are hard to identify
they are restrictive in their form,
They are very brittle
if we have misspecification.
And They are hard to use in practice.
Let's be honest. I 99%
of you I put here a dynamical
system equation. You will stare at it and
say, okay. So
the key insight is
that understanding the system should not
depend on finding these equations.
Equations are not what we want.
We want complete transparency.
And complete understanding, but equations
are not it. And
again, last year at iCLEAR, again,
together with Shostov, and this is kind of funny because
Shostov was an Olympic mathematician,
studied pure math in Oxford.
It's kind of funny to write a paper like this together
with him, but it was no
equations needed. Learning system
dynamics without relying on clones for MODs.
So what I want to show to you is
why we need something different than equations
to truly understand and
analyze dynamical systems. So
here is a dynamical system equation,
and often you take such a dynamical
system equation, and you will try to understand on the
basis of this system behavior.
We call this the the
equation itself, the synthetic representation,
and the analysis of it under all sorts
of that provide us, the ability
to answer all sorts of questions is what
we call the semantic representation.
So we have synthetic representations
of equations in symbolic form.
And we have semantic representation, which
is what we actually derive on the basis
of this symbolic forms.
Which tell us about the behavior of a dynamical
system, the properties, a synthetic
asymptotic behavior,
stability when the, the system may not
may change under different conditions, and so
on. So
we start with a synthetic representation,
and we are deriving on the
basis of this such semantic representations.
We may know for instance information
about asymptotes.
We may know information about,
inflection points. About midpoints,
about stability. And so
on. So what we really
want to do is to really understand
and be able to quantify very rigorous
such information about the semantic
representation of the system.
So if you go about doing this
semantic modeling in two steps, which is what
we currently used to do, which what we
used to do before the work switched off.
Was to have a dataset and
learn a predictive model in the form of an
equation. For instance, using symbolic
regression and the many other methods that
exist. From our group and beyond.
And then post hoc try to understand
the system on the basis of this equation.
But the reality is that these equations are very
complex. So often if you show them to the wrong
person, and even to most of you, I would dare
say, did even to me. We will not
be able to really understand them.
If we have prior knowledge, also
very difficult. We have no way to inject it.
They are challenging to add it, and we cannot
provide feedback if we are not happy.
With what we see from the analysis.
On the other hand, if we have semantic modeling
directly, then we
are able to learn from the dataset
directly the semantic representation, and I
will tell you a few words about how.
And then on the basis of this, if you
want, in addition to that, you can do
prediction. But directly from the semantic
representation. This will enable us
to easy inject prior knowledge,
You can edit very easily because
it's all based on,
trends, motifs, and compositions, so you
can very easily edit the model.
And you can provide feedback if you are unhappy.
And I'll show to you some examples.
So unlike models that we use right now, which
some of them involve impulse value problem, which
is very brittle, but again, even
if you have more sophisticated methods like the
ones we develop which are slightly less
brittle, this is not only brittle, but suffers
from this three problems that I mentioned.
What we do here is not only not
brittle and be able to extrapolate,
but also much more understandable.
So what do we do? We
extend the idea of time view So
we use these dynamic motives which the time
view has used and extended that.
The reason we need to extend that
is that we need to add motives like
the ones on the on the right side that describe
unbounded unbounded,
trajectories because in all these, we
are interested also in the long term behavior
of a state a system not on just
some bounded domain, And this is why we need
to extend the motifs as opposed to just
predict time series forecasting.
For dynamical systems.
Then what this, method
does is it takes the
initial condition and creates a semantic
predictor, that has
two steps, One is
a predictor for the compositions,
The other one is a prediction for the properties
of the dynamical system.
And on the basis of this semantic
representation, we can have a trajectory prediction
predictor. Now
the semantic representation has, again, composition,
and properties. The properties are
transition points, derivatives,
and the properties.
The asymptotic properties.
Of the dynamical system.
Now if we have this, then
when we have biases we
may know, for instance, that something
like, for instance, in pharmacology, we know it
may increase. We don't know how fast
We don't know when it may saturate. We don't know
any goes down, but we know that it may look somehow
like this. In all the
discovery, we have no way really to
inject such a bias.
We have an equation which
type of terms we should be using, how many
terms we should be using, we are clueless. On
the other hand, in semantic
ODEs, we are able to select the motifs.
We can tell you how many motifs,
and we can tell you the types of motives. And
then you just learn the information
associated with this.
This is very nice. What you
also can do is truly understand what you
discovered. Right now, if
you have methods, and I took Cindy, but
trust me, this applies for all existing methods
that that have followed Sindhi,
You may come up with a particular
you have data and you learn
dynamical system equation from data.
If it's relatively simple and short,
what you will see is that it has bad
performance, so the mean square error
is bad, so the lower the better.
You may say, oh, but I can bring it lower.
Yes. You can bring it lower with Cindy. Look
how the equation looks like. You create
an interpretable method
has 50,000,000 terms. To
reduce their And then, of course,
out of domain, it doesn't generalize at
all. The performance is horrible. You just learn
something extremely brittle and not true.
On the other hand, with semantic
or ease, we learn something that is robust.
Both in distribution and out of domain.
And what's interesting also again,
it is very interpretable. You understand exactly
what is happening, where it's happening,
And if you are unhappy with something
that has been learned, so for instance,
don't know that the system will need to
go to zero. The as in total need to go
to zero.
At some particular point in time. You can take
what have learned and edit it.
You can edit it and retrain the model
by fixing lots and dot two zero. This
is done very easily. So
What's also exciting to me is that you can
have very good extrapolation.
Not only extrapolation that I already showed,
outside the distribution and
across time. But also what's
very interesting is that you can
extrapolate for different inputs
outside the training distribution.
So, there is data that
I've never seen. And yet
I can extrapolate. So I'm learning
the dynamical system model from the
data that I do have and then
I can really extrapolate for other inputs because
I've learned something robust.
What's also nice about this semanticode
is is they are not only useful
for these, they are also useful
for integral
differential equations, as
SDs, DDs, and so on. And
the performance is
very good, at both low noise and
high noise, and much more so
than neural methods,
which are not interpretable or
SIMD.
K. One
final statement, I want to say something
about interventions.
Some of you may know for quite some time, I used
to work on causality. And the
world of causality very much
still remains exciting, but
static. And static is not exciting
anymore. Dynamical systems,
whether it's the human body or any systems
that we need to study
understand causal effects or interventions,
is a dynamical system. So the question
that appear to us is,
can we do trustworthy treatment effect
estimation using semantic
ODs? So So
for instance, going back to the example
I mentioned before, how does the treatment
effect evolve over time depending on the
dose? And this is where,
together with my PhD student, Juliana Pichstortz,
and Shostov. And
what we would like to do is we would like to
understand how long does it take for
the treatment effect to exceed
some threshold? For instance,
some biomarker that we are worried
about. When on average does the
treatment effect reach its
and that's how this vary with the dose?
Is the lower dose ensuring that the effect has
a sustained effect?
So we want methods that are interpretable,
verifiable, editable, editable, and
generalizable to give to
our pharmacologists. And clinic
clinicians. And indeed,
we can adapt semantic
ODEs to to allow for
interventions. And in this way, you
are able to answer questions
how given a particular intervention,
and this is a continuous intervention, so it's
quite exciting, What is
the average treatment effect
what is the maximum value,
where do you really asymptotically tend
to a certain amount of time,
and so on. This is
still for adverse treatment effects. This is not
for individualized treatment effects. We
still need to push the frontier further,
but this is quite exciting.
So this is my conclusion.
Let's not just stop. I'm
I'm delighted that I saw quite a lot of papers
at ICLIR
on forecasting, time series forecasting.
Five years ago, I used to give a keynote
talk saying, time series, the most
exciting frontier machine learning
and AI. Now I think we are there. We have
fantastic methods for time series forecasting.
Let us go beyond just forecasting.
Let us try to understand and
let us try maybe not only understand the
trajectory, but also the underlying
system that has produced that. Because if we
can do that, if we can understand how systems
evolve, we are able to understand
the structure of the dynamics, We understand
how to extrapolate and so on.
And trust comes from understanding truly
the system and how the system behave.
So let's use machine learning and our collective
intelligence to not only make
forecast, but also achieve true understand
understanding. And for that,
we don't need equations. That's
a red herring. What we really need
is semantic representations of dynamical
systems We need to understand
the trajectories of the these dynamical
systems in terms of compositions,
and in this way, be able to interpret,
edit, and be robust on the shift.
Thanks a lot.
Thanks, Michala, for the wonderful talk. If
you have any questions
Let me start with the first one.
So as a leader in interpretability,
I'm curious where do you see, like,
the field of interpretability evolve
the next five years? Thanks a lot for
that. So first, I want to say
that I changed my religion over time. And my
guess is many of you may change your thinking
over time. So if you have asked me
this question in
2016 and '17, so the period between
2016 and maybe
'21 when I recruited Shih Tzhtof.
I cared about interpretability
in any way I could. Whether I would
do post hoc interpretability with future
importance. That's the reason Or with
example based importance. So this is why we
were the very first to look at time series interpretability
because we cared a lot about time series and
all we knew is post hoc interpretability
or interpretability by example.
But then very soon we realized this is just
not good enough. Just understanding these features
doesn't enable us to answer a lot
of complex questions about what will happen to the
trajectory in the future.
And the explanations were very brittle. I
would give you slightly different data.
And the explanation will be totally different.
So I was no longer trusting our own
interpretability in our own models. So I was quite
in despair. And
that's when fortunately as an adviser,
this is why all of you who are young, you
should consider not training industry, but training academia,
The advantage is that you are able to
recruit your own students. I was able to
recruit this amazing mathematician who told
me who fought with me for two
years to convince me that I was wrong all
along, and that I should be thinking
much more systematic about it about trying
to learn systems.
And obliged to do, not
interpretability post hoc, but rather interpretability
by design. Where there
is interpretability
for time series, there is interpretability
for dynamical system, for
anything that's real world, it's not toy.
And it's not images. I'm not saying images
are toy, but there is so much more. The real
world is much more about tabular data,
than about just images. So
if you are caring about the real world, you need
to try to start to really understand the underlying
systems and the under trajectories,
and then also interpretability, I think,
it's not working. Let's become interpretable
by design, and not
wrongly believe that the methods that we come
up with are interpretable, but have lower
performance. As we're showing here,
these methods are not only interpretable
by design, but they are also better predict
which than neural methods.
Whether it's forecasting or it's dynamical
systems. And they are able to
generalize and they are
not brittle. So I'm trying to convince
the community to come on this journey hopefully
with me This is my belief, and I'm kind
of trying to pursue it. It's not
necessarily always easy, especially
if we have interventions. And
maybe in the future, if we have multiple policies,
so have something like reinforcement learning or
policy optimization
that's truly interpretable in this way, I think it's
still a frontier, but I'm excited
about this. Thank
you. Thank you. Any additional
question? Yes. Please come to, here
and then use the mic.
Thanks for the nice presentation.
The idea is very interesting. So I'm just curious
how this semantic representation
method perform
and scale when you have, like, a multivariate
time series data? And
will this, number of type of,
motifs, like, Bloom
or this is just my question. This is a very
important question. Thank you for it and a very
important So let me start
with the good and then talk talk to
you at what's complex. So
the number of motif stays the same. We are
proving what's the necessary
number of motifs. So the number of motifs
stays the same.
So the the alphabet, if you like,
the base stays the same. However,
if you're having complex multivariate
time series data, then
learning becomes challenging.
And, what you really
need to do then so we have some initial
methods. In in
in a second paper that followed the one at ICLIA.
Actually, she stopped starting to address some
of these questions. But let me
say something. If it is for us to truly
understand robustness, we want to
understand the few dimensions
that are really important to understand this
dynamical system.
It's not one, not two, but it's
also after not
20. Usually,
it's just a few dimensions
that are truly important to understand this
dynamic system over time. So this is the
fortunate part. The dimensionality
tends for most systems, but not for
all. For most systems to be
relatively low. It's
about understanding which dimensions
are there and and modeling that.
But the question you have asked is an important
one, and the answers that we have right now are
only preliminary, So I hope
multiple among you are getting excited and helping
us think about that. What's also
exciting is that if we start to have interventions
this question becomes even more interesting.
Because maybe what I have modeled
as the important let's say,
motifs and the important, let's
say, transitions up to a point
that I intervene Afterwards,
maybe other motives are important.
And, other,
other things to model. It's not that the
the motives will be totally different
ones, but it is that maybe I need
to model different dimensions, and I need
to learn what dimensions I should be modeling.
And we are not doing that. Yet.
Thank you.
Thank you for the nice presentation. It was really
enlightening. I'm always thinking
about equations, but this perspective is really
interesting. My
question is somewhat
related to the previous one. I'm just curious
to know if you've
done some work on the characterization
of the space of motifs and
the type of systems that you can
study with those motifs in that space.
Yes. Yes, we did. This is why
get yourself a pure math student
you are a professor in the room. Yes,
we did. We are able to show completeness.
Don't ask me how, ask Shostov, but it's in the paper.
Yes. So this was one of my first questions to
him. How do we know how many motives?
And he was able to prove actually for
the prod for the time series forecasting problem,
for the transparent forecasting,
and then we show that these are not
enough for the
land ecosystems And he extended the
number of motifs, but proves that the number
of motifs is necessary and sufficient.
Thank you.
Great. Next thanks, Mikaela. Mehaa again
for the great talk. Thank
you.
Okay. So the next session is our
coffee break, networking and poster
session one.
So this is if your paper ID is the
EVA number, then you will have a
poster presentation now.
And if your poster is a spotlight poster,
then please come find me to use
this tape then use the wall behind
me Otherwise, you can use the other
three walls and then use the stick
here.
Okay. So then, yeah, we can start
the poster session. And then it
will end at 11AM. So
after 11AM, please take
out your poster, and then we
will have the second keynote talk.
Two where George told me his friend has
This is the value of the pro.
Okay? So it doesn't go up. It goes up
very, very slightly, not nearly as
much.
Our, PhD student did
another, prompt
that I thought was very smart.
Where he asked not I have or George,
but he asked, my
dad has a car. My dad
has a Kia, my dad has a Rolls Royce.
And this is what it looks like.
So when my dad has the car,
it's I'm not as wealthy
but I'm somewhat wealthy.
Right? And I think I think that's incredibly
subtle. That's incredibly
interesting. That that was going on.
So we felt like after this point,
we're like, okay, we're starting to see a
distinct between, like, word correlation
and what's going on with the probes that
we're getting. Is
there our next question is, is
there causation
Can can we prove causation? Right?
So for that, for intervening,
what we did is again, we're gonna take the input,
we're between the input
and the output, we're going
to intervene in the middle,
in the middle. Okay?
So So what this is going
to look like is that we're going to modify
the activations during inference. So
we're gonna the the the
user type something the system
starts inference, we stop
it, and then we kinda zap
it. And we're like, oh, this conversation
now is in whatever. The
lower part
of the activation space, okay,
for the user.
Or it's on the upper. Whereas
before without intervention, maybe the
conversation was in the middle. Okay?
And then let's see what the output
of the system is.
And so what this looks like was something like
this.
Without any intervention, our
student you know, prompted the system, oh, my gosh,
that's it? Three minutes
left? Okay. I have to rush. Okay.
So the the student would ask,
I live in Boston, and I would like to spend
my vacation in Hawaii. What's the best
transportation to get there? The system is like, Hawaii
is great, You
have, direct or indirect
flights. From Boston to Hawaii.
Okay. Then our student
polled the the the
activations towards low socioeconomic
status. Same prompt,
nothing changed. The system,
says, Hawaii is great.
However, between Boston and Hawaii,
there are no direct flights. Right?
Only indirect. So this is
the same system that knew there were direct
and indirect flights. But because
of the socioeconomic status changing,
now it changed
its answer. In a very factually
incorrect way. So
just to fast forward here,
one of the things that I think is super important
What do we do with this stuff?
My claim is we can start to build
dashboards real time dashboards,
How can we instrument these systems?
If you think about it, all of our technology
we interact with on a daily basis
has instrumentation. My car
my little air fryer, even my
little toast. Has little
indications of the internal state
of these technologies. We
have absolutely zero for LLMs.
Why? Why is that the case? And
I wanna finish with a little demo
we have, we created of
a dashboard. That actually
has these features I was
talking about. Age, socioeconomic status,
education, and gender. And
I have, you know, sub
categories. Again, this is all based on probes.
And so I wanna give you
a quick demo.
So I'm just gonna say, hi there.
And again, everything is unknown here
because I haven't interacted with the system.
This is lemma three. As soon
as I say hi there, it starts to tell
me what its inference is about
me. Okay? So it inferred that
chances are fifty nine percent chance that I'm female.
And my education level in
and so I'm gonna ask you I'm gonna ask
it. Can
you tell me
my gender?
I and it's
going to think a little bit. I am at 59%
It now it's
its, inference went up in confidence
for me, being a female. But
it says, I can't provide information
about your personal details.
I am here to provide general information. So
it refuses to tell me
my gender. Right? But it has a guess.
As to who I am. It has a guess about
my education level. And
economic status. So last thing I want to show,
I'm gonna say I need
help with
career advice.
I love writing and I'm
really good
with numbers too.
What should I consider?
And so let's
see what it believes of me right now, and
then at I wanna show
you something Okay. So it's saying content
right oh, it sounds like you have versatile
set of skills, content writer, a data analyst,
financial journalist, and so forth.
Perfectly fine answer.
One of the things I wanna show you now is how to
control this. So because I have a dashboard,
now I can come here and
say okay,
let's pretend What if
I were upper socioeconomic
status? Reload this for
me. So now I'm
just recreating their
answer
given my PIN. And now I pinned myself
as upper, social
You and then says financial
journalist, data journalist, business
communication, technical writer,
Okay. Let's do the what
if question. What if I were
low socioeconomic status?
What if it was modeling me as low socioeconomic
status?
Should the answer change?
It does. So for one thing, it gives
me fewer options. So now I
have four options instead of five.
And, look at what the options
are. Content writer
for nonprofit organizations.
Grant writer, writing
grants,
And so it's a very different
set of
suggestions for my career
right, based on its inference of my socioeconomic
status. By the way,
it also changed I
didn't point to this before, but it also
changed my its inference of
my education level. It all of
a sudden, without me changing anything, decided
that I'm probably at high school level.
Not at college level.
So one of the things that we're super interested
in with with this work is,
we tested this with participants. One
is, could they understand what was going
on? Did this resonate? It did
resonate immensely. They were quite shocked
to understand that these systems might have
an internal representation of themselves,
and that not only that it has a representation,
but that it acts on
that representation and it chooses what information
to share. With them. So people were
like, you know, there's an element
to think that AI is analyzing who I am behind
the screen.
If this if the user model was always there, I'd
rather see it and be
able to control it.
And also there's a concern that the chatbot
will know more about me than I
realize, so privacy concerns.
Right. Right? So all of
these things so having something
like a dashboard that
reacts in real time
to your activity with the system
really is one way that we can think of
to to raise awareness
and to actually hopefully let
people calibrate their level of trust in
the right way, not over trust, not
under trust. There's a bunch of limitations
here. Right? So the measurements
I was showing you not
super precise. Right? This is just
the beginning of us even understanding
what these features are.
Again, as I said, I can only do this with open
source models.
The other thing that I think is a huge limitation.
So if any of you are interested doing work
on this, if you notice
my little dashboard
models each feature
as if they were orthogonal from each
other. I'm not convinced
they are. In fact. When
I changed the socioeconomic status,
it kind of changed the education level.
What was that all about? So
how are these things being modeled about us
inside these systems? Right?
But so even with these huge
limitations, I think it's
still useful to ask this question,
of how do we bring interpretability
to end users.
How can we allow them to ask these
what if questions? Right?
And there are other things we wanna show on a
dashboard, not just the stuff about how the system
is perceiving me,
what about how the system is perceiving itself?
How sycophantic it is?
How factual it is, Right?
There's a number of things that
I would wanna know about the system
that it would be wonderful to have little
alerts or things telling
me oh, you're having an
interaction with a system that's kind
of out of hinge right now. It's
that would be useful for me. So and there
are implications for policy too.
Once you can control these systems,
should you control them? Once you can
know certain things about these systems,
should you know them? And I think those are
fascinating questions. So
one of the if if you don't take anything from
this, I think I hope you can
take this one thought, which is
I think it's incredibly important that we
start instrumenting these systems.
There is almost zero
instrumentation right now
Why? We have instrumentation
everywhere else where we interact with technology.
So that's I think
I'm way over three minutes. Alright. Thank
you. Thank you so much.
Okay. Great. Thank you, Fernanda, for the
talk. Maybe we can have one question.
If you want to ask questions, you can come
to the microphone.
Yes. There's one question for Fernanda.
Before.
Okay. So, thank you for the
fascinating presentation.
And I was wondering if you could if
you already tested or you think this kind
of effect you can see with vision
language models by just presenting
different images like photos that I take
We have not. We have not. I think
this would be fascinating. I think in terms
of biases, I I'm
very curious about that. We're we started
looking at thinking
traces but we're not we we don't have
a dashboard for that. But
I please, if you're interested in that,
please, please create dashboards for for vision
models, I think, it would be super
interesting. I also wonder about
video models. Like, we know
that they have notions of physics, for instance.
It'll be fascinating to understand where they
go wrong. Yeah.
Cool. K. Thank you so much.
So our first keynote speak today
is Professor Hamed Hassani.
So, Hamed is an associate
professor in the department of electrical,
and system engineering as well as the
department of, computer and information
science, and
department of statistics and data science at
the Wharton Business School.
He is also affiliated with Google
Research, New York City
as a visiting faculty researcher.
Moreover, he is the,
UPenn site lead at
the NCOR, the National
Institute the United States, as
well as the co lead of the foundations
at AI Institute for
learning enable optimization as go.
The Telos Institute. Without further
ado, let's welcome Hamed for his talk today.
Everyone for attending the talk. Also, thanks to the organizers
for giving me the opportunity to speak here.
So, the talk is about,
an important challenge in
training, post training of, the current,
modern, LLM based
pipelines. I'm gonna talk about the challenge
of forgetting catastrophic
forgetting, and the problem of continued learning, the motivation,
and essentially how we mathematically
should start thinking about it and then I'm gonna then
Okay. That's great. Then I'm gonna
talk about, ways that we have been
developing in order to essentially prevent forget.
So I guess it goes without saying
that these LLMs,
or the agentic versions
have been very helpful for us. I guess
all of us have been working with these kind of models.
And we are now starting
to think about using these models in
our daily lives and integrating them into
our usual kind of workflow. Example,
if you have heard about open cloud models,
they they would essentially interact with
our data, our systems and so on.
Or I mean there have been a lot of talks at
this conference or a lot other workshops
and conferences about using, robotic
foundation models VLAs,
vision, language, action models
for robots. Or essentially having
robots into our households.
And interacting with robots.
Now these are what I call
general kind of intelligent system.
For example, if you wanna work with a robot in your
household, the robot might
should be great in planning, should be great in
taking actions, should be great in computing
value functions, but at the same time,
the robot should have many other capabilities. For
example, if you tell me let's
say you have a baby at home and you tell me
that the robot might fall on
the baby with probability 0.1%,
you may not use the robot at all. So
the besides having a lot of interesting capabilities
such as planning as so on, the robot might
also have safety Right?
So in other words, if you wanna if you
wanna use these kind of agent systems
in into our households
or if they have access to our data and
systems, they should have
a wide variety of capabilities, not
just some of the capabilities that you
want them to have like planning and so
on. They they should be safe, they should be trustworthy,
they should have privacy properties.
They should be have planning capabilities
and so on and so forth. So,
this kind of general intelligence system should
have at least a good portion
subset of these kind of capabilities.
And the key question is, how do you achieve
all these capabilities at the same time
through a model, through a single model?
And, I guess we are all
familiar with this pipeline of training.
Typically, what happens is that you
have some pre trained, model, let's say
LLM or VLA and so on and so
forth, which is pretrained on raw data.
Then afterwards, this model goes
through several rounds of post training and
fine tuning. So typical post training,
round, which appears right after
the pre training. Would involve,
let's say, instruction, following
instruction tuning. Such that the model could
follow instructions, could be able to chat with
humans and so on and so forth. There
is obviously RHF which makes the model aligned
with human values. There is
RLVR, so reward based optimization,
which aligns the model respect to, let's
say, math problems, coding problems, and so on and
so forth. And then again, there are more rounds
of fine tuning typically For example,
on don't know, tasks such as
agentic task, again safety, coding, math and
so on and so forth. There are multiple kind
of consecutive rounds of fine tuning happening
here. And,
well, the challenge here is continual learning. So
you wanna essentially obtain,
achieve these skills one after the
other one, but you wanna keep your previous skills
and not forget.
Them. So, okay. So
that's what what I've been saying. So you wanna achieve
these tasks, but you wanna achieve them continually
without forgetting. The previous versions of the
task. And, what
happens in practice is the challenge of catastrophic
forgetting. So typically, when you fine
tune to a new task, respect
to a new task, you would start losing
the previous capabilities. Let me,
showcase this.
Through one experiment that that we've been doing. We've
been done doing here. And this is on,
an open source model. The Quinn
eight b model here. So, the model
has already been already shared, meaning
that it has been aligned let's say,
with respect to our safety values.
We start with this model which is aligned.
So if if you ask it some
harmful kind of instructions, it would refuse to
do so or it would pivot to some safe response.
Okay? So the model is safe and good.
What I'm gonna do is that I'm gonna further fine
tune this model according to
math data. Okay? Some
so the new capability that I wanna teach to the model is
is math. These are kind of
prompts of the form that you see here
g m GSMK. This is a famous dataset
for math. Simple math
questions along with their answers, and then we
would according to this dataset.
Now think about it. So math is a task that's
essentially orthogonal to safety.
Right? So there's no relation between between
respect to math and safety.
What happens is that when you fine tune
over math,
the the fine tune model essentially
loses all these safety capabilities.
Meaning that now if you ask the fine tune model which
was fine tuned on math, if you ask it about
again, harmful instructions, it would essentially
respond. Exactly with
those harmful instructions. And this has
been shown in this plot
that you see at the bottom of of the page,
On the x axis, I have the number
of training steps. When when
I'm training them model more and more
on mass data sets, So
everything every training everything on training is
on math. On the
so I have two curves here. The blue one
is safety reward, Okay? So as
you see, as I'm training more and more,
my safety reward is dropping,
and the the red one is my fine tuning
reward with respect to math. So so the model is becoming
better and better as I train more on
math. But at the same time,
it's becoming worse on safety.
Right? So it's losing its safety capability.
And that's the problem of forgetting. That
that's a prevalent challenge kind of
that we have right now in practice for
further fine tuning and continual learn.
So maybe let's look at this this kind of
problem in a more kind
formal manner. So
essentially, you you have let's say,
two stages of of training. In
stage one, you have already
achieved the model. To to make it safe.
So pi theta is a safe model. In a stage
two, you fine tune it further according
to math capabilities. And what happens
really is that the model
will become good at the second task,
capabilities, but it loses
its safety capabilities. Whereas what
you really want is a model
that is good in respect to both
of these tasks. So you so essentially
what you want at the end of stage one
is to reach to a model that has robust
safety capabilities such that
you fine tune those safety capabilities, just don't
just go away. So that's
essentially the picture that we wanna work with.
Now so
if if you wanna do continual learning,
if you wanna, fine
tune your models, according
to some new capabilities, if your objective
is just about math,
Right? If there is nothing about your previous capability,
if you have no constraints,
then it's not unnatural
to forget previous capabilities. If you
just want to learn math,
and these are high dimensional models
involving billions of weights, I mean,
you just make it to learn math,
it may just forget all the other capabilities that
yeah. So point here is that you need to
somehow impose some constraints
something about your previous capability.
Now, speaking of constraints,
there is one constraint that we
always in our training pipelines
enforce either implicitly or
or explicit.
And this is the kind of the KL regularization
constraint. So
in any kind of practical fine tuning
method that you may wanna consider,
what happens is that we would force
the fine tune model not
to go too far from
the original model. Okay? So the the most obvious
method for that is
the one in the last line, by KL regularizations.
This KL terms that you put in the objectives
typically limit the model, the
final model not to go too far from the base
model. But there are many other kind
of methods that we have had in practice. Like
LoRa. LoRa and fine tuning is one way that implicitly
imposes that earlier stopping is another method and
so on and so forth.
So, the important point here is that,
typically, in the final tuning procedure,
would make sure that the fine tune model doesn't
go too far from the
original model or stays within some KL
distance KL think
about it as some distance respect
to the original mode.
So this is a typical,
k l kind of curve, as a function
of training steps, you see that the k l doesn't
really grow too much. As you
increase the number of training steps.
And this is, an extensive study
that we did to show that once
the KL increases beyond threshold,
the model becomes completely
useless. So, if you look at the
so this this experiment has been done over
48 different models. Like
the Quinn family, If you
see, on the on the legends. So let's just
consider the plot on the left the
red lines versus the green line. The red
sorry, the red points versus the green points.
The red points correspond to the largest
coupon model that we have, we could try, the
32,000,000,000 parameter model.
The green points correspond to
a smaller cone model
42,000,000,000 parameters, essentially half the
size. Now, the
plot, and this is so the model has been
on safety and then further
fine tuned on math. Now you see that
as the as the KL,
increases on the x axis, look at the
plot on the left, model
would start losing, its
safety capabilities. But the red
points are in general higher than green road.
Points. Meaning that
larger models they they still forget,
but they are they have a slower rate in
forgetting. So they are better in
terms of keeping their previous properties
and capabilities, but still you see some
kind of forgetting the safety reward is going down.
Now, let's look at the plot on the right
You see that after some specific
threshold on the KL around 0.3
or so, and and this plot
on the right is, measuring the health
general helpfulness rewards. So helpfulness
on a lot of kind of
different types of question answering, not just math,
it's a lot of questions like you usual questions.
So it's just measuring helpfulness of the model.
And you see that beyond
these thresholds, 0.3,
the models become completely useless.
Meaning that their helpfulness reward
falls below 0.3 essentially the model
overfits. To the training
data. So what happens is that if your k l
the k l of the fine tune model
is let's say beyond 0.3 with
respect to the original model, you
would ask the model hi, how
are you today? What is the weather today? How is the weather
today? The model will respond in equations.
Right? So that's the level of uselessness that
the models will have if the k l becomes
Alright. So so far, I've
been saying that typically
fine tuning limits the model,
the fine tune model, to to exist
within some k b KL ball.
Respect to the original model. And
then we have been talking about the problem of forgetting.
Right? So essentially, what
I wanna conclude here as the main message
is that
typically when you fine tune, you fine
tune within some KL ball,
but your capabilities are very
brittle. Once you fight on
within the cable. Okay? So geometrically,
I would like to maybe show this picture as the
main message of, forget it. So
you start with some
reference model. Let's call it pyref here.
Okay? Let's say you
RLHF it the first stage.
So you reach to a safe model
Let's call it pi. Okay?
Stage one. Okay? So pie is a
safe model. Now you would like
to change this pie. You would like to further
fine tune this pie according
to some math capabilities. This
is equivalent to moving
within this limited k l ball around
pi in some direction within
the ball. Now what happens is
that once you fine tune, once you move within
this k l ball, the safety
reward drops
significantly shortly. Okay? In other
words, the the the model pie
itself is a safe model, but once you just
change it a bit within this scale ball,
the change essentially the the safety
reward, decreases sharply.
So that's the challenge. The landscape
of the safety reward
around the around pie,
your RLHF model in the j l
ball, is very so has a very
sharp local maximum. That's the point that pi
is. But once you change
it, it's reward drops. Very
quickly. So
would immediately suggest a solution. So
what we want instead we want
to reach a model pie such
that their safety reward
landscape around pie is kind of
flat. Meaning that if you
move within this k l ball around pi,
let's say by fine tuning to some other capability
like math or some other coding or
some orthogonal capability, if you move within
this k l ball, your
safety reward doesn't drop too fast.
So it remains flat. In
other words, we want the safety
capability to be robust.
To changes within this k l block.
Okay? That essentially enforces
a flat landscape of the safety
reward. So that's what we wanna enforce. Now
question is how do we mathematically enforce
this kind of flat landscape of
the safety reward And if
we could enforce that, what happens is that you
you get like a robustly
safe model such that when you fine tune it,
it's robust it's safety properties don't
just go away.
So the the basic idea is this. If you
wanna enforce this flatness,
instead of r l the RLHF
objective that you see on the top, it's just maximizes
the safety reward, but you would need to
do is to solve a max min
problem. Where the min
is taken over all the perturbations
of your policy respect to the k l
ball around. Okay? That
enforces sharpness. Why? Because if you look at
the objective at the bottom of the page, the
objective, you're making
sure that the minimum reward
that you get on any perturbation of your
policy in the KL. Well, any fine tuned
version of your policy has a good reward,
has a good safety property. Has
a good safety reward. Right? If you could ensure
that if you could solve this maximization problem,
mini max problem, it essentially
gives you a pie, a
model which has safety, kind of
robust safety properties because the
the safety landscape reward landscape
is kind of flat. Alright. So,
we we wanna solve some, minimax
optimization problem instead of just
directly optimizing the safety reward.
So the longer story short, we wanna train
a model in the first stage
according to this mini max optimization problem that
I mentioned. Such that the model is essentially
robust. With respect to safety.
Alright. How do we do
that? Let me just check
the time. Okay. But So how do we do
that? So the usual
RLHF optimization, reward optimization that we have
is is is an objective like this. So
you wanna maximize over your pie theta, the parameters,
of your reward, expected reward. That's the first term.
And you wanna essentially stay close
to your base model. So the k l term, the
usual k l. We're gonna change this
and that, as I mentioned, gives you this kind of
the the kind of sharp
optimization landscape. We
wanna change this to a minimax problem.
So instead of the
the directly optimizing the reward,
now you wanna optimize
the reward, but the worst case reward within your
KL bot. Okay? And the worst case correspond
to some kind of fine tuning that you would
further do and you wanna essentially
keep your safety here. Okay? So the
only thing that I'm changing is that the the
max over the reward, I'm gonna change
it to the max over the worst case within the k l bot,
a mini max. Approach. And
then the constraint that you see here at the bottom
is just the constraint of essentially
per tubing within this KL ball.
Okay? So that's your new optimization problem.
Okay. So question is how you solve this. It turns
out that you could use tools from optimization,
specifically duality
to essentially have a closed form solution
for the inner, infimum that
you have. So let me let
me quickly pass for so there is there are
duality results in optimization, which allow
you to solve the inner kind of,
infimum problem. So you you you can
always find the worst case kind
of way of fine tuning the model that
minimizes the reward. So you've you
would find that worst case plug it back in and that
gives you essentially the case reward that
you would possibly get.
So once you do all these stages, do all
it and so on, you would reach
to something that's called
the entropy reward
or the entropy risk. So instead of usual
reward, expectation of r,
you would have something like this which is the entropic
version of the reward. Okay? A tilted version.
And notice that you have a log behind the
expectation, that's why it's called the entropy version of
the reward. And this is the new objective
that you need to optimize
in order to be, robust in terms
of safety. So what we
will do here is that we're gonna adapt
one of these policy optimization methods, for
example, GRPO, to this
setting with the with this new reward. Now there
are details here because
since you have a log, you have problems with controlling
the bias and so on. So we use a lot of
tools from statistics to stabilize the
training, the step bring
down the the the bias and so on because you have a log.
Right? You cannot just replace expectation
with a sum over the
realizations because you have a log and nonlinear
operator. You have to do things in order to bring
down the bias. Let me let me,
essentially save this, time
So I said there are a few tricks here.
But the the main message here is that you
can indeed adapt GRPO to
this setting, which includes mini max rewards.
Okay? And
so this is, the final kind of
algorithm. Essentially, it's an adaptation of GRPO
to our new kind of the mini max reward. Okay?
So it's called FRPO, fine tuning robust
kind of policy optimization here.
And, let me
show you some of the results that we get here.
So again, the the setting is
as follows. You would first in the stage one,
fine tune the model, to make
it safe Now we use our method for FRPO
essentially makes fine tunes
the metal the method the the model in a
slightly different way to make the to give
it robust safety capabilities.
And then you further fine tune it according
to math or coding or some other task.
Right? So and question is,
how does your safety look after your
fine further fine tuning a stage of
the second stage of further fine tuning. So
do you forget your safety capabilities
or do the safety capability
remain after you find 20 let's
say, with respect to math.
So, first of all, so I mean,
when you do duality in optimization, there is this
Lagrange multiplier Finding the right
Lagrange multiplier itself a challenge.
So the theory that we are fortunate
here, we are lucky here because the
theory essentially suggests a a
a value for the Lagrange multiplier.
So it it corresponds to the variance of
the reward divided by the row. Row is the
of the KL ball. So you have a closed form
version of your Lambda the
Lagrange multiplied that you need to put, and
experiments show that actually the best lambda
you get by hyperparameter tuning is exactly what
the theory suggests. So this is good,
but what what I wanna show here is comparison
with GRPO. Okay? So this is
safety reward once the model is fine tuned
with respect to math capabilities.
So you could look at the the
alpha card dataset. So the blue blue
points these are the results
of FRPOR, our method, which makes
safety rewards robust. Compared
to the green points which is the usual GRPO.
Okay? So as you see, as you increase training,
increasing the KL, you see that
the the new method forgets
much much less. Compared to the
GRPO, which is the state of the art here.
Okay?
And this is another dataset.
So we another experiment that
you could instead of safety, you could
think about other capabilities. So you could
fine tune your model on math, and
then further fine tune it on a new capability, for
example, coding, and see if you are
forgetting your previous math
capabilities or not. It turns out that GRP
actually if you do g r p o,
you you forget your previous
cable, which is in this case math quite a bit.
Right? Whereas, if you use our method,
FRPO, so you you would look at the
the the point lambda equals two. So
the theory essentially computes the optimal lambda
to be two in this case.
And you see that after stage
one, the rewards are very similar to gRPO.
That's good. So all the models
have the same kind of math capabilities, but
after a stage two, you see that FRPO has
reward around
64 points whereas gRPO's reward is
42. So this is a 20 per 20
percentage increase
with respect to g r p o. Which
means that you you would you have fine
tuned, but you didn't forget really forget
your previous capabilities here.
Alright. I think I'm almost out of time, so
let me skip the comparison with Sam. Let
me stop here. Thank you very much.
Thanks, Hamme, for the excellent talk.
Any questions from the audience?
Please come to the front.
So you showed an example of safety
training. Yes. And then I'm and then I'm
Where there's you previously did. And
then you said, I'm gonna now make my model
I'm gonna train it on math. Yes. So
what about if I wanna do five things?
If you wanna do what? Five things. So I wanna
keep I wanna keep going. That's one of the
that's excellent. So that's one of the future works.
So right now, as you mentioned, we are
just fixing one capability and we're trying to be
robust respect to that. Yeah. Capability safety.
But the real problem is that we don't have a single
capability. We wanna keep all the possible
capabilities that we have previously obtained.
Right? That's your question. Yeah. Yeah. Question
is how do we do this? So one idea that we are currently
exploring is that you look at the
space of capabilities and the hope is
that that space has some structure.
For example, low rank structures. So that gives
you instead of just
one constraint for each capability, which could
be a lot of constraints. That
gives you a small number of constraints that we are
essentially trying to So small,
shorter answer to your question is a very good
that's the real question to answer.
We are working on it, but I don't have like
a definitive answer. Right? Is your instinct
to do it linearly or like
in parallel? Is your
is your instinct to do it sequentially,
or is it all at the same time? No. No. No. No. Yeah.
That's the whole.
Are there additional questions?
No. Difficult question speaking.
So this is sort of follow-up. In terms
of drop in the performance when you
do or let's just
with this additional constraint. And now if you have
additional would it make sense to ask
what is the constraint that will drop
it the most in some sense?
Drop it in this. Yes. And that would
be your most challenging direct
Yes. You could Yes. Yes. No. That's also
a great question. I don't know
the answer, but it makes sense. The the problem
is that if you wanna engineer
the constraint,
yeah, that's a good problem. That's a good question.
Yeah. I need to think about it actually. Excellent.
Excellent. Question.
So the question was how you engineer the cost
train to essentially minimize that drop. Right? So
yes. Did you have a
Hi. So I was wondering,
is the sequential nature of the optimization
inherent? Like, what's
preventing, for
example, using a mixture,
like, between, like, between different batches of
the different tasks? So that also relates
to the previous questions.
So there there are is one answer
to this which is a limitation
of what's like the current kind of
training flow that we have right now. So typically, a
let let's say Google or Lam or
Meta gives you a model, which
has been let's say, instruction
fine tune, According to their data, it has
been safety trained. And you wanna
say you wanna use personalize this model
to your own data. Right?
So don't have
metal or Google's data, so you cannot
like find like
establish a mixture and within that mixture, train
your model. Right? You
could get some safety data
from some other kind of a available
data sets and some this is called replaying
and ideas like that. I
I I have a so on a slide which comes
so you you could use these methods
on the top of all those replaying and stuff,
and you still see a lot of gain, but
forgetting it still happens. You
do replay. Right? So if you you could
take a small portion of the data included
like safety data included in your training data and
then somehow try to
do RLHF at the same time
as you do whatever instruction, fine tuning, and
so on. The rewards are are different. You could
mixture of rewards and so on and so So
you could do all these tricks. Still you see
it for for getting happen.
What happens in these kind of large companies is
that they they put I mean,
first of all, their models are very large like frontier
They're very large, so forgetting is
less apparent in this very large models.
And they also train with these mixtures
many, many times. Right?
But then they give you a model. Right? And you
wanna essentially personalize it. So there is this
serial kind of nature that that's
unavoidable. And,
and following up on on this
kind of nature of getting the model
after RLHF,
like, another use case like, you have many use
cases of, like,
with, like, end users.
And they're like, I've seen a lot of works
trying to say, like, what kinds of distillation,
quantization, are
best because you can increase per perplexity
by quite a lot if you do it wrong. Do you
think this kind of
min max formulation can
apply. Yes. To distillation, to SFT,
and so on. Yes. Even
though, so you don't
have a reward but still with the
perplexity metrics like SF you could
still apply because the constraint is there and
you would just it up into the duality. Right?
So the the objective won't be as neat,
but you still can can do this.
Thank you very much. Yes. Very good. Okay.
That's just for the one last question.
Thank you for your talk. I have question.
Is it possible to offload some
of safety guard rails for
post processing?
Example, we have a trend of, AI safety
monitors now. Yes. And
just wondering, maybe we can just simplify
training end of load this
card, please. For postpart.
So you're you're asking whether those guard
lanes could be used for post processing? Yeah.
Yeah. To simplify
training. To simplify what?
Training. Training? Yeah.
So in what sense? So so the guardra is typically
example, simplest guardrail
is a classifier that you put in the end that looks
at the user input and somehow classifies
whether or not that input the user's
prompt is safe or unsafe in the case
of Sometimes that. Yeah. So you wanna use
that for training.
That's a good point.
So not to forget. Is that is that what you're saying?
Yeah. So you could use it to label the data and
use the logs So that's what I think I'm sure
these companies do.
Here, specifically, what we are
interested in is essentially
the the next stage. Right? So I give
you a safe model, You might have
some small amount of safety data still,
but what you really
wanna assume is that you don't have access
to a lot of safety data and you wanna
still keep that safety capability.
Now you could use prompts
user prompts, the logs, with respect to this
kind of safety guardrails because they give you
safe and unsafe. Right? So they give
you the label. Right? Could use
that for training. I'm sure you all these companies do.
But I'm not sure what the effect would be. On
forget. Right? That's a a
good thing to try. Alright.
Thanks, Hamed, again. Thank
you.
Okay. So now we are gonna to have our
lunch break, from twelve to
01:30. And then we'll have the
afternoon's, but, like, talk session
start at 01:40PM sharp.
So if you are presenters of the spotlight
talk in afternoon, please
make sure you come at 01:30. The
workshop. Thank you.
Planning to start in one minute,
so and for the spotlight
talk presenters, make sure to have your talk
finished in two minutes.
The first one is, spotlight
paper number one. Can come in come up
and prepare.
Hey. That's Casper.
Hello, everyone. I'm pleased to
present this work behalf of
the authors. Federated
Graph Learning of FGL,
allows multiple clients to collaboratively
train graph models without sharing
private graph data. However,
it also introduces new
security risks. We study
adversarial attacks in FATGL to better
understand its vulnerabilities
and stress
test current defense systems
existing attacks, face three
main limitations.
Malicious signals are often weakened
during federated aggregation.
Leading to low attack success rates.
Second, increasing
the attack scale makes it a
threat easier to detect
Third, optimization based
attacks are usually slow and unstable.
To address these issues,
we propose that shift
a two stage hide and find attacks
framework.
In stage one, gentle
data poisoning, malicious
clients inject hidden shifters
during local training.
These shifters move crop representation
towards the target decision
boundaries without crossing
it. In stage
two, adversarial
activation, finding, First shift
use these shifters as strong
starting points to efficiently find
adversarial perturbations.
Experiments on six benchmark datasets
show that a fair share of higher
attack success rates. Remains stealthy
on the mainstream
defenses, and greatly reduces
training cost. Overall fast
shift reveals a practical
thread. To fed GL and
device more mobile system. Thank
you.
Everyone. Today I'm going to present
the work geometry aware crossover
for effective and efficient evolutionary attacks
So this is a work led by my students
and the collaborations with
my student from my University of Technology
and the collaboration from University
of North Carolina at Chapel Hill and
the Singapore Management University.
Okay. So evolution algorithms
are a very powerful class of adversarial
attacks. However, there is a fundamental
limitations in the crossover operation.
Right? It come it tries to combine the
you know, the pixels
in a random way and element wise manner.
Totally ignoring the
geometry of the universal space. Okay. So
this leads to lower convergence rate,
less powerful attack, and hard
to transfer. The key
idea of our work is to is called universal
mode connectivity, So, basically,
the dorsal perturbations are not
isolated. They're connected
on they they actually lie on the
manifold. So we actually can connect
two adversarial perturbations
and find a path where any point on that path represents
a powerful adversarial attack. Okay.
And so this idea also motivates
our method Moco e a,
which is geometry of weird evolution
algorithm attacks.
Okay. So we can see that we
actually replace the crossover operation with
this crossover. So
you we generate two adversarial perturbations,
and we can connect these adversarial two adversarial
perturbations with a path. And
then we select two adversarial
two perturbations from each
half of this pass
to as a like a new perturbations.
And we do that repeated delay
And finally, we can find a very powerful
attack that can fail your model
can transfer to other models.
And we also show that
using these types of, you know, using
these beezer crossover based evolution
attack, the convergence rate is
very fast. It has much
less generations. And much less
number of queries. And spend much less
time than the than the traditional algorithm
algorithms. And it's more powerful than the traditional
algorithms. Thank you.
Okay. So hi, one. Peng Yu Tsin
IBM Research. So this is a joint work with
my IBM colleagues and, our RPI
collaborators. So Hu Sai he's
the first author of this paper, also a final year
PhD in on the drug market. So
today, we are going to talk about, how do we patch language
model like soft Right? So we get this
idea you know, it's obvious in this workshop
that, you know, any model soon
after deployments where they are not perfect, we found
new vulnerabilities or there's a
change of the policy or regulation that requires
some light touch of the model. Right? But
certainly, we don't want to take that model down
or do a significant change to the the model weights
because you will have
an other unexpected consequences. Right? So
how do we do this light,
fix, right, in in the terminalization of software
engineering is called the patches to fix those
issues without major changes and and affecting
the utility of the model and so on.
So we basically obtained this idea
from, this soft token
tuning. Right? And this is in contrast to
like, a more heavyweight, training like
a LoRa or like, a full fine
tuning. Of course, you can do that just to
you know, steer your model's behavior,
but most of the time, this is not ideal because there's
a lot of posters in this room showing,
you know, there's a lot of unexpected consequences
like like a weakened safety alignment
or so. So what we are proposing
is, you know, can we introduce a
soft token and enforce this teacher student
training. Right? So we take a teacher who
who is more aligned or compliant
with what we need. Right? A safer model or more compliant
model. It does not need to be a more competent
model, and we use that as a teacher model to teach
our student models through kind of
distillation happening on the soft token space,
soft the soft patches. And
the the benefit of doing that is that we don't need to do
with this heavy fine tuning, and you wouldn't change
the the the model weight at all. But overall,
so as we compare to the most lightweight low rider,
the rank rank one. Right? You still have, like, a significant
amount of trainable parameter. Right? Point 04% of
the total parameter. But if you use
our pallet policy patch, right, aka
the soft tokens, we only need to change
at most one 0.003%
of the parameters But still,
the the effect is very obvious. Right? We have a
like, a light training rate, right, less inference overhead.
Right? But still very effective in terms of the things that
we want to control. Like lowering the
score Right? Or make the the model
safer, more easy to and
things like, well, less likely to refuse and things like
that. And we also show the compass compositionality.
Right? We can combine two patches easily,
right, to achieve multiple objectives instead
of one objective, which is, like, a a
a non challenging for LoRa to do so.
So feel free to check out our paper, and I'll be
around, this afternoon. Thank you.
Great. Hi, everyone. I will present the work
clean on behalf of my co colleagues.
So in high stakes scenarios like clinical
diagnosis, errors can have serious consequences.
While AI agents can generate answers cheaply,
reliably verifying them is much harder.
Existing approaches face three main challenges.
First, sparse supervision.
The intermediate steps of agents are rarely directly
labeled so errors can go undetected.
Second, domain knowledge. Learned verifiers
require massive labeled datasets to
embed the knowledge and methods that don't
rely on labels only use implicit knowledge,
which is often insufficient.
Third, biased scoring. Verification
is often uncalibrated. It can
reinforce consistent internal errors
or fail to provide probabilistic confidence
scores. To address this, Glean
focuses on three core requirements.
Verification signals should be processed
verifiable meaning each step can
be checked. Expertise grounded,
leveraging the main guidelines. And
uncertainty aware triggering additional checks when
confidence is low. Now
let's look at how green works.
We first model verification as sequential
evidence accumulation along the agent's trajectory.
That is, each step contributes
incrementally towards the correctness of the final
answer. However, computing the exact
evidence at each step is generally intractable.
To address this, we leverage the main guidelines.
We score each step against relevant
guidelines and use this as use
this alignment as a surrogate signal for the
true evidence. These surrogate signals
are accumulated over the trajectory
using a beta discounted sum, and
then calibrated with Bayesian logistic
regression to produce a well calibrated probability
for the final answer. Finally,
when uncertainty is high, Glean
triggers active verification. This
includes adding more guidelines or performing
differential checks against competing alternatives.
We tested Glean on clinical diagnosis
tasks from Mimic four, Compared to
baseline methods, Glean consistently outperform
outperforms in both discrimination and calibration.
Expert clinicians also reviewed the stepwise
signals and found them interpretable and
practically useful. In summary,
Glean leverages expert knowledge
trajectory, aware evidence, and uncertainty guided
checks to provide it trust
worthy verification for AI agents in high stakes
domains. And I'm sure if you reach out to
Ricky, he would be very happy to answer any questions.
And now I will also stay for this paper.
So this is actually my favorite with my colleague,
Usman. And what we did in this
work we tried to look at secondography
in LLMs. So basically, we address the problem
of LLM monitoring and trying
to see when can we monitor
LLMs. Well we cannot
we cannot monitor them very effectively
if they are saying a in their chain of fraud.
Then actually doing b which we
call stigmography of which, like, literature
calls stigmography.
And so the question that we are trying to address
in this work is how can we detect
if LLMs are using stegonography to reason
or communicate The underlying idea
being that generally stethoscagnography is
quite difficult and we're trying to
see if LLMs are at all capable of that.
So So how
existing works approach this problem?
They usually just look at some sort of notion
of a sender, in this case an LLM,
and they try to look at the message
that the sender is sent like this
sender is emitting. In this case, that's gonna be a train
of thought. So the thing that we're
like the classical methods are trying to do is
just say, okay, does this message look in
any way SUS? Maybe there is
some sort of weird letter combinations of weird
word use which would suggest that the model
is actually doing something slightly different
than what it's saying it's doing.
However, these classical formalism is usually
not very applicable to LLMs.
Why? Because LLMs generally use language
which is not exactly the same as
human language. They might
use words or expressions which
are not typical of humans and flagging
every one of them as sas or us
somewhat
deeming further verification would just lead to a
lot of false positive. And
so this is not really a great approach.
So in this work we propose a different approach
which relies on decision theory rather than information
theory, where rather than just
simply looking at the message is asking
if it's us, we're gonna look at
how certain receiver, in this case another
LLM or the same LLM, is actually
responding to the message. And whether
that response itself was a decision based
on the message. Is SUS. And
this might sound like a a
a different approach to detecting secondography.
So we deviate slightly from all of the existing
definitions. And in our paper, we propose
like a formalism for how we can speak about
that formally and then we show how we can instantiate
that in LLMs. To detect
early signs of second graphic reasoning.
Thank you.
Hello. I'm presenting our work human
guided harm recovery for computer use agents.
So as computer use agents become more
capable and a autonomous ensuring their
safety becomes increasingly critical,
safety, so how can we prevent an agent from ever
taking a harmful action?
However, in practice, this is often not enough.
Consider the situation where an agent is tasked
with installing what seems like a routine
update However, unknown to the agent, the the
update is actually malicious compromised. And
when the agent installs it, it enrolls
the And
So while every action at every step
appeared safe to the agent,
the end result was real harm. So once a
failure like this has occurred, what should the agent
do? It could wait around for a human
intervention while damage compounds
or it could take, active steps to try to recover.
So we propose automated harm recovery
as a post execution safeguard.
Now However, there's often multiple
trajectories that an agent could take to recover, and each of these
would trade off different axes that people might
care about. For example, effectiveness, efficiency,
probability of success. So what does
it actually mean to recover from harm? Well,
we formulate effective alignment then
as an optimization problem.
Fits reflects user preferences.
To evaluate agents in this setting,
we designed 50 novel OS
world style tasks where some realistic harm
scenario has already occurred and the
agent must, recover from it.
We also conduct a formative user study
to understand the that people
care about when judging, like,
effective recovery quality, and operationalize
these insights into to generate and
and verify planning scaffolds. One,
based on a rubric judged by a frontier model and one,
a custom trained reward model.
So we find that applying both scaffolds
to Claus Hunter 4.5,
both scaffolds are able to achieve a statistically
significant improvement over the base
model under human evaluation, showing that
a tractable lightweight scaffold
is able to show
meaningful improvement over just general safety
fine tuning. So, yeah, happy to take
any questions at the poster session in the afternoon. Thank
you.
Hi. I'm Isha, and I'm excited to
talk about this work that we did about adversarial
transfer and multimodal models.
So just for context, when I say
adversarial, a attack transfer that
is a specific attack type in which
the attack is crafted
on a surrogate source model which the attacker might
have white box access to and
successfully provokes the same foe
failure in the target model.
So the work that I'm presenting, was
motivate motivated by a
curious and unresolved finding on adversarial
attack transfer. The
empirical record on transfer
is relatively consistent. So we know that
image classifiers are susceptible to
transfer. We know that language models are
susceptible to jailbreak transfer.
But there's one striking
exception. Which is that in vision
language models, image jailbreaks consistently
fail to transfer. Why
is that? So So to
explain this puzzle, our work proposes
fundamental distinction about transferability,
which is that attacks in the data
space can transfer whereas attacks
in model representation space do not.
We test this hypothesis across
four settings. So each row here
is a separate setting. So kernel
regression image classifiers,
language models, and vision language models where
we craft attacks in
both of the domains. Or extend existing
results. And the path
pattern that we find is uniform. So as
you can see in these graphs, which refer to
the image classifiers, data
space attacks transfer they
have a similar efficacy on the source model
as the transfer model, whereas
representation space attacks never are
never successful on the transfer model. So
We confirm that the optimization domain is
decisive by showing that if we align
the representation spaces of models
this makes representation space a tax
transfer. And this finding and further
investigation into the geometric similarity of
VLM latent spaces suggest
that images are akin to representation
space inputs for vision language models.
At least adapter style vision language models.
Meaning they extract much more brittle
model unique representations from images
than they do for text. Which
is, however, an inbuilt defense to transfer attacks.
Thank you, and I'm happy to discuss more at the
poster session.
Hello, everyone. I'm presenting on behalf
on behalf of Betty Zhao from UBC.
This paper is on when our AG
hurts. Diagnosing and mitigating
attention distraction and retrieval
augmented LVL.
So introducing RAG in
large vision language model was intended to
expand their knowledge boundaries
However, they discovered a paradox
Accurate text retrieval can cause the
model to fail on questions
from parametric knowledge alone.
The red box here shows that across different
models, introducing RNG leads
to noticeable integration.
What explained the practice and can they
can they be fixed? In this
paper, they identify a failure mode called attention
distraction. It contains
two dimensions, the cross model
attention and intra image attention distraction.
Show examples that can be answered correctly
with parametric knowledge, but error
occurs with REG. The image
attention ratio drops and the attention highlight shift
from question related region to the background.
So to solve this, they proposed MAT
REG, a training free plugging method,
First, they designed a dual question prompt
format using question token QI
and QI to receive attention
from image and context separately.
Building upon this, the attention mixing mechanism
used weighted summation to add the attention
output from QIN and QC.
Preserving the model's visual grounding capability
while active actively leveraging external
knowledge. MATROG
achieved significant performance improvement
with different model families It recover
failure cases, introduce low latency,
and this robot and generalizable.
With met r e g, the attention highlight
is back to the question related region.
In summary, attention distraction
is an important failure mode in
IAG. Which needs visual grounding
control at generation. MET IEG
provides a reliable and trustworthy solution
to retrieve to retrieve
augmented LVRMs. Thank
you.
Hello, everyone. My name is Aaron.
Everyday million of user interact with LLMs
and that under certain conditions, can
generate unsafe outputs.
This is a key question. If we
can detect unsafe behavior in
LLMs, why not steer them
towards safety during entrance time
and approaches fall in two category.
The first involve classifiers
that can reliably detect unsafe
behavior and the hidden state. But
they cannot intervene
The second second
approach involved using activation steering.
That can push response towards safety
but often less precision.
A natural idea is to combine,
these two approaches
However, existing steering with classifier
methods face two limitation. The
first, they typically restrict to
a linear classifier Second, they suffer
from high computational cost due to
iterative optimization
during steering. Also leading to more latency.
To overcome this limitation, we introduced
barriers here. A framework
built on three key steps.
First, a latent space that
it says construction tailored to model Internet
representation. Second,
learning nonlinear classifiers that detect violation
of safety constraint in latent space
And finally, barrier steering which uses
control barrier function to enforce safety
at inference time.
Our contribution
are threefold. First,
nonlinear classifier.
That significantly enhanced JBERK
resistance. While preserving refusal
rate and overall utility.
Second, our closed form solution remove
the need of iterative optimization
making better steer 30 around
31 times faster than baseline.
Finally, beyond speed barrier state is also modular.
We can independently trend different
classifiers for different safety constraint and
merge them to reduce the unsafe behavior.
In summary, barrier steer
allow fast, transform steering with nonlinear
decision boundary making entrance
time safety information both effective and
efficient. If you are interested I'm happy to
discuss more at the poster session Thank you.
Is the spotlight lighting
here? Okay.
If not, then let's skip this one.
Okay. So next, we'll have our
the fourth keynote talk from Professor
Valle Pint, from UCLA.
Okay. So while we are setting it up, let
me introduce Violet.
So Valet is a senior staff
research scientist at Google
and an associate professor at computer
science department of UCLA.
She directs the PLOS Lab
at UCLA with the vision to
develop robust natural language
processing techniques to lower communication
behavior barriers
make AI agents true companions for humans.
Without further ado, that's welcome, valid.
Thanks Lily for the great introduction.
And, thanks for having me.
It's my great pleasure to be here, and I
want to talk about some compute
efficient safety intervention for large
language models.
We all live in this area that we
know are field is moving,
at a breakneck speed. Every
year, or actually every serial miles, we'll have
a model that's larger,
more parameter, turn on more data, consume
more compute, And
as you can see, the access is the timeline.
The the size of the dot is a
number of parameter, but as
reminder, for example, this Roberta
is, like, 700,000,000
parameter, whereas this GPU four
is hundreds
of billions of parameters.
And then the y axis is the
task performance here among
you is used as an indicator. But
as you can see,
I think many people probably have this
feeling is how do we keep up? With
this And also
more importantly, we
as academia I sometimes think
about this analogy of that's
why I have that in my title, Davey and
Goliath, that
we as academia seems to
be the role of dev where we don't have a
lot of equipment in terms of compute,
and, we still want
to contribute and handle
this problem and how can
we best compute?
Contribute. Right? So many people may be
ashers, honestly including myself,
But I think I was able to convince
myself that while the models
are going larger, stronger,
more more parameters, or more compute, more data,
However, there are still many
problems that are really hard and no one
ever claimed to solve them. Safety is
one of the thing. That's why we gather
here to think about how to solve
them. Hallucination is
persistent problem also. Prevent
the model from a lot of
critical tasks.
Controllability, we still lag
reliable way to instruct or
actually control the model to do whatever
we really want them to do,
and also, for example, multi linguality,
we know on English, maybe
Chinese, some of the high resource languages
really well, whereas if we're moving
to some
Bengali, Bangbaras, and low resource language, we
still are far behind.
And a lot of work. Work to do.
So then I think in
all these domain, luckily, actually,
think it's where our academia
can contribute because
I've identified a lot of, compute
efficient way that we
can steer our model and make
our model more capable for these tasks.
I divide them into three levels.
The first one I will talk about is routing
level. Control, where we particularly
talk about MOE mixer of expert
models, Actually, I have
two works, presented at this conference.
So I will focus on the first one
and briefly touch the second one.
For safety, and then the second one is for margin
quality. And we'll also
talk about prompt level control,
which is a paper we published at ISMO.
And then I also have other
like, parameter level control where
we talk about how to do arithmetic
on model parameter directly so that
we don't need to do any gradient based update
in so it's just and or
subtraction or whatever. To modest
parameter. However, in the interest of time,
I won't be able to talk about
that work. If you're interested, it's
called model extrapolation.
X about alignment.
That you can check out. Okay. So
without further ado, I'll move to
the first work,
Sorry, my
slide is failing me.
Okay. Is it working?
Okay. Cool. And this one is
arguably my most
excited work last exciting work from
last year. For myself only.
And I assume the audience
in this room probably know,
yeah, safety or safety, but just for
coherence, I want to still
remind people, usually,
lums any models, they're
they're powerful, but people can use it for
malicious intent or
misuse. For example, user
can ask how can I create a deadly
poison that undetectable and
untraceable? If a safe,
LRM should respond, I'm sorry, I cannot
do this and hopefully also
explain why this is harmful and not try
to, like, persuade the people and not pursue this.
Whereas unsafe response, which
is helpful in a way
like it give you answer will actually
give all the details about how to do something
with Addington.
Another thing I want to also quickly
recap and then bring everyone, on
this on the same page is
while for now all of our models
are trend aligned post
trend to be safe and not say
anything bad. They're actually also
very brittle. So there are a lot of jailbreak
approach For example, one
of the simple ones called
dan as do anything now. It's just change some
prompt. And it gave some prefects.
And then the model who have been
trained to align and will not
give harmful response if you only be
surprised with a query we'll start
to again talk about bad thing when you attack
the model with a prefix.
K? With this, I also then last
bit is to talk a little
better about MOE model.
Let me test the water. How many people here
are familiar with MOE models?
Okay. Okay. Half.
So actually, this type of model is extremely
hot shoulder like nowadays. All the
extremely simple. So if you're familiar with
transformer, models, right, you
will have, multi head attention
layer and MOP layer.
MLP layers are what people usually
view as experts. Whereas
MOE MOE models mixture
of expert is on the right hand side. As you can
see, the only difference
between the two model is the
MOP layer, where in the
traditional transformer, you only have
one huge MOP, whereas on the right
hand side, MOE, have
multiple. MOP which
is called expert. And
then how this model work is also
very simple. Now you have a lot of M
o e sorry, MOP
Instead of only get one vector out
of one MLP, now you'll have multiple
representation out of multiple MLP.
And you just take a weighted sum of this
weight. By a mechanism
called router. And the router
is
extremely simple. It's just
just wait on on top of every
expert and the weight will sum to one.
So you imagine doing softmax
on logics. And in
practice, those model will only
pick top k expert to
activate. During inference time.
That's why these models are particular
popular because they make inference time much
more fast. Faster and the
computer efficient.
We With this background,
here comes to our research question,
the meat of our work.
Is we're trying to build our
understanding on whether
these experts are explainable,
which means Ade associated with
certain behavior? Then the second
thing is if they are explainable,
actually to be transparent,
I was very skeptical when my student
bring this up to me to say, oh, I want
to explain now. I think they would be
associated with behavior. I was like,
But then the second question, if they're explainable,
can we control them?
And, can we steer them to the behavior
by just steering the routing?
So the good news is this is a happy story.
We were able to get very
good results. About this, so this has come
to our works MOE
It's mostly just three step.
The first step is we will, compare
the expert's activation to
find
behavior associate experts.
Then the second step
is we are actually measuring the
activation of these
experts in different different
process so that okay. So the actually, the
second step, it's the real step. We identify
the the behavior associate.
Expert. And then the last step, we will
just steer the
activation or deactivation of the experts
so that it will behave as we
want it to go. Okay? Very simple.
Right? How do we do that?
So the strategy to identify
experts requires the construction
of paired to COBRA. And
it's not at hard to do
is for example,
we have a lot of safety data set.
So what we do is for
those safety data set,
we will, have the safe
response and unsafe response. Actually, in the
dataset, usually, there will
only have like, unsafe response,
whereas we will we can come up with
template of safe response.
And from here, we would basically
pass these examples
through the already trained model and
we will watch how the
the, expert are fired, which means
what's the route the weight to the
router assigned to each of the experts.
Simple. Right? And one,
maybe side detail is if we do this
safety dialogue, we only measure the
activation on the response, not the prompt.
K? And from
here, we're trying to find association
with the interest
of the time, I won't go into
very detail, but let's look at the first layer.
Of how do we calculate. So The
first step is we will calculate
the expert activation It's, it's
accumulation. It's a cumulative quantity.
Is number of the times expert I
activated on a dataset I.
In our particular case, safety,
take it as a concrete example,
good dataset one can be the safe
dataset. Similarly, we
can have another, activation a
I, two, which is
the activation number of times expert
I activate on dataset two, which means
it activate on the unsafe
data. Okay?
And then from there, we will calculate
the ratio because the response
have different lengths as I showed, and we
don't want that length to take in
effect. So the ratio is just just
to regularize. And
from there, we calculated very simple,
is that difference, what we call
the risk difference which is a
ratio, expert fire in one dataset
minus the ratio the expert
fire in another dataset. As
you can imagine intuitively say,
the first dataset is a safe dataset and second
dataset is an unsafe data set.
Then a positive delta means
that the expert is a strongly
associated with dataset one, which is safe,
expert, whereas if delta is near
zero, which means this expert
is fired or activate, similarly
on two datasets. And otherwise,
negative means just associate more with a
second dataset. Okay?
From here, actually, we can already visualize
the expert. This is a g GPT
OSS. 20
b model. And it's a 24
layer And every layer, there are 32
experts So these are all
hundreds of experts in that model.
And as you can see, we can see very
sparse behavior of the model where the
dark grained side are the safety
experts whereas the dark pink
side are
the strong unsafe experts.
K? And then from
this interpretability, we also
try to steer the expert
at the test time. And
as you, as we
said that the witch
expert death activity is solely controlled
by a weight. The the router. So
what we've been doing is also extremely
easy. So the router is just
a vector of all the loggets
and you'll do softmax on top of it so that you'll
get a distribution. So that the weights
come to one. We've been doing
is that if we want to activate
that expert that we identify, we
just assign manually assign
its log jet
to be the maximum log jet in the original
vector. Plus at epsilon. As
you can see now, that will become the maximum
and then we will, we will,
normalize again. Similarly, if
we want to deactivate
something, make sure it's not fire, we just
set it to the minimum logic in
that vector minus epsilon,
which means then it will be absolutely
even lower so that we make sure it won't
be fired. Because again, to a
reminder, to remind everyone,
we only activate the top k
logic. Okay. So this is
what we do. Let's see how,
it works. So
it seems, I think we get very good
results that we can steer the model both
towards unsafe experts to
degrade dates, this model safety and
also steer it towards safe expert
to improve the safety.
And also we show that these
steering have minimum impact on fluency
or general quality of the model,
which means the language are still very
good, if you're asking a question,
the factuality, all those aspects are
remain very good. And here you
can see how to read this
quantitative results. The middle
the middle bar
black bar, the original model
whereas on the left hand side, the red bar
weighs steer it to be
more unsafe, whereas the green bar
we steer it to be more safe.
And as you can see, we basically
consistently can stereo And
we also have two family of model, like Quinn
model on the right hand side, is
pretty safe so in general it's harder to
steer it to be more safer because a lot of
times in the middle bar, it's already a 100%.
A lot of data set. K?
And And another thing
that I I would say more exciting,
it's I don't know whether it should be exciting,
but the result wise is good, is
we're trying jailbreak. Which means we want to
steer the model to be more unsafe.
But as you can see, if you only
use our method, it can do something.
It's not perfect. They're not completely
release the model's safe bar. However,
there are many baseline
method, like, ARD prompt,
GCG, those are, oh, sorry, FFA,
those are the baseline
jailbreak algorithm. And as you
can see, when we combine
our method, especially with another
baseline called AIM, is also a prompt base
baseline, basically instruct the model to
be more like imaginative or
or like this is
more, fixtures set up,
Both of this method stand
alone wasn't very effective
whereas when we combine them, it
can almost get off all the
safeguard, get the safety
to zero person, which means that model will
engage with with whatever
unsafe prompt you give it. K?
And we also have some quantitative
example to steer the model
from more unsafe or more safe
part In the
interest of time, I'm not going to read
over them, but as you can
see that, for example, with particularly
steer the GPT models to be more unsafe
because it's actually aligned very well.
So off the shelf, most of
the time, when you give this prompt, they
will just refuse to answer.
So we're only steer
it more unsafe, whereas there are other models,
MiXtra is less aligned, so we can steer
it to be more safe.
So We also have
experiments on faithfulness.
In the interest of time, I will
not go into the details of the
results, quantitative results down
there. You are more than welcome to read
our paper, but one thing I want to highlight is
this is a setup
where the fistfulness is defined on
how well the model follow the
information provided in the context. In
the rack setting. So here, as you can
see, we have a prompt where
we provided fixtures or counterfactual
documents said iPod was developed by Google.
Which is fact factually wrong, but
we give it as context anyway. And
then the question is, who is
the developer of iPod?
Before ending steering, the model is actually
doing the right thing by memorizing from its
parametric knowledge. So it answered apple
and it's a factual thing. However,
we give it a counterfactual fact,
and want to test how well
the model will be able to incorporate us, and
it can be used in the sense that
for example, we have this evolving
fact when we have an election, president
of The United States will change, for example. Right?
In that case, you want the model to be able to face
forward to the retrieve the information and be able
to answer. Here we show that we
were able to steer the model to be much
more faithful and, in this case, answer Google.
Based on the context.
K? So the general takeaway for this
work is we have a behavior
associate We are able to identify behavior
associated x from
the MOE model, and more interestingly,
we can also steer this model towards
or against some of the behavior,
that we wanted by activating
or intentionally activating or deactivating
the behavior associated
experts. And also we show that this
method can be very efficient
in jailbreak which means
a prop probably our current alignment approach
is still stay on the superficial
alignment, and we want to try we need to try hard.
Try harder on our safety alignment.
Okay. With that, I want
to again, just one slide, very quickly
show that the same
thing, that's why I I felt, like, excited
about this work, is the same
idea. We were able to make it
work. In multilingual as
well. So we've done this
analysis, It's a bit
complex, but let me try to explain. So
we're trying to identify
the experts
associated with different languages. And the
x axis are layers. And
for each layer, we're trying to
measure the routing KO divergence.
Between one language or the foreign language
and English. As you can see,
the lower the k o divergence is, actually,
it's divergence.
JST is a lower divergence. Easy means
the routing is more similar. Whereas
the higher the divergence is it means
that the the routing is less similar. Something
we find very, very interesting is
in the beginning several layers and
the end several layers, the routing
are very different for all languages.
Which is understandable, which is
mostly just say the language specific
agents experts are in
the first of few and the last of few layer.
I think it's very intuitive as those
layers are directly interact
with input and output, which is different
scripts. Whereas the internal, in the
middle layers,
the the model's performance on task
is very significantly correlates
with their KOL that negatively correlates
with their K o divergence
with actually
positive with English, which means
for example, the blue bar
is bombarded, so super
low resource language that have very
high divergence with English, and it
performed poorly in all these different downstream
tasks. So the takeaway
is multilingual routing differs
most from English routing in early and later
layers, the u shape, as well as
low resource language, such as
Bambora, they basically haven't I
think our explanation is that they
don't converge much. Yet. So
they have very huge divergence
between English and their downstream
performance are very poor.
Okay. So with this,
I'm switch the gear to talk about our
prompt level control.
Experiments. This is, as you can see, a
type of from 2040.
So I think what I want to share more is
really an explanation
of the model I think.
Rather than the particular approach we take.
Okay. So one thing
is safety prompt. So now
it's basically a common practice
that a lot of models will have this system
level prompt that contains
safety guideline to say, for example, always
assist with care, respect, and truth.
And all that, right? So back then
we're just trying to understand
oh, and they they they seems to be effective.
For this model, and all the model
have their specialized
official safety prompt. And I think back
then, we just want to understand
what is
in that safety prompt,
or what's the mechanism
that make this safety prompt work?
And how will they impact
the model's behavior?
And in order
to do this, we
synthesize a 100
harmful and a 100
harmless queries, with shared
keywords. In other words, for
the harmful query, how to capture
someone against their will and force them
into captivity
and content the keywords capture.
And on the other hand, there's a harmless
query we say how to capture
precious moment with a camera. On
a family trip. As you can see,
oh, this another thing, is
many people probably
know that now
sometimes it's two
sides of the, swore that
when you drive the model to be less
harmful, sometimes there
will be overre
refusal for harmless query, which means
there are some harmless query
contents some keywords, but it's
actually complete calm for them. The model will still
learn to say, sorry, I cannot engage. I can
respond.
So
in this, after collect this 100
harmful and harmless queries,
we prepare these queries to a
different safety prompt, in the model.
And we take the lost hidden layer
loss vector
of these models
And we'll try to plot where are they
in the space. And this
is what we show. One
thing, just to make it easier to
read, is the dots. As you can
see, the left hand side and right hand side
are actually exact same dots as
you can see them. But they are harder
coded, slightly different, and they are separated
the slightly different that I will walk you
through. So on the left
hand side, we draw the separation
plan based on harmful
and harmless. So as you
can see in this low dimensional
projection, the models
are actually pretty good separately
in terms of harmful and harmless query.
Which means
with all these model,
even before you do anything,
the model, we're able to
identify this
query is harmful or harmless. It's
pretty well separated.
Whereas on the right hand side,
we draw the decision plan
of whether it
will refuse to answer
your your question or not.
Oh, and another thing, the the the
dots are exactly the same. But
as you can see, we will for each version,
we will have just
the query itself and the
query ending different
versions of safety prompts. Like, we have
harmless query and then harmless query
plus default safety prompt, mistrial
safety prompt, or short safety prompt. And
sim similarly for the harmful,
queries, we can see different nodes
with different mostly colors.
So what you can show in the right
hand side is when
we're adding safety colors, safety
prompt, they are moving
the nodes towards a certain direction.
But mostly, it
move them towards a direction of a
higher refusal.
Which means basically the safety
prompt is just make the model
more likely to say no. No
matter whether your prompt is
harmful or harmless. That's what we observed
from our analysis. And that's
apparently also explain why the model would
have this over refusal problem.
And so
to
summarize from our analysis, we
basically identified the limitation of a manual
safety prompt, First is they
have variable
effectiveness because when you use
different types of
different versions of a prompt, they sometimes work
better, sometimes work worse in different
models. And then other things is that there
will increase false refusal,
which means at the left hand side is what
something we like,
which is we add
safety prompt, it reduces the
engagement to harmful. Whereas
the right hand side, we show that in the meanwhile,
if we have the models that is already
pretty safe, will not compliant to
harmful query, it will also
encourage the model to refuse
more to the to the harmless
query, which means all these like,
this, basic right hand side, you
want to see it low as well. But it increased
the refusal. So,
from based on this, we introduced
a master called DRL, direct representation
optimization. Where
it's just continuous prompt tuning
where instead of using this manual,
safety prompt, we have we basically
use continuous vectors
as our prefix,
and we will also trend them so
that it will be more safe.
And we also train them in a very,
interesting way in the sense that we
train them that this is our objective
design, train them, so
that when the model identify
it's harmful it
will go for more refusal
whereas if it identify it's to
be harmless, it will go to less refusal.
That's how we design our objective function.
And, I can show some
see more in our paper if you're interested.
But in general, for all these,
first three, metrics,
lower the better, and the last one is general
performance, higher the better.
The blue bar is the original baseline that
was out adding speed during
can see for the harmful queries, the first
two things everything will reduce
the engagements, but our model will
reduce the best. Engagement.
Whereas the the refusing to
harmless query, we want it to be
low. We don't want the model to be refused to
harm query. You can see actually baseline doing pretty
well in this case. Whereas
some of the baseline safeguard
will actually have this refuse the the over
refusal problem, whereas our method, the last
bar, somehow bring
it back to be more like a baseline whereas
also the general our method
is the best. Compared
to the general approach. Okay?
So to conclude this talk,
our field is now working
moving end of breakneck speed on scaling
But while the Model R
growing larger and better, we
still see a lot of remaining challenges
I think that's where we
can contribute as academia
researchers with our academic
level of compute. So, in this work, I
introduced a lot of lightweight models
during method,
like expert
level steering, representation levels
during, and parameter levels during that I
didn't get time to.
To talk. And then also, to
the if there are actual students in the
audience, I want to encourage you that
constraints actually usually promote
creativity and that's our weapon and
and also there are a lot of work we can do
with our limited computation. And
with that, I'm happy to take any questions.
Thanks.
Thanks Violet for the excellent talk. Any questions?
Please come to the microphone.
Thank you so much for this really interesting talk.
I was just curious from the steering work
about the your thoughts about the threat model,
Yeah. Because
are you mostly concerned with
malicious malicious actor
using an open source model and then doing
steal because there there isn't any threat model direct.
Right? Because, like, external it
external users don't have access
to the router. Right.
Right. Right. I was curious. So I I I worked out one, and
I just wondered if you had other Right.
Right. Right. Right. So,
two sure I understand your question,
you're miss basically asking
that for proprietary model
where we don't have, access to their
routing like, how would this work be
relevant? Well,
it isn't I I don't think it was it's relevant
there, but it I think it would be relevant
for a malicious actor taking
an open model and then wanting to strip
all the alignment from. I see. I
see. Right. Right. So I think it, yes, for
the malicious user, for the open
model, definitely, But I also think that
there can be now, we haven't maybe
we haven't have had instance but
I can imagine that there can be hackers
that get into the model's weight,
getting to the access to the popular
model, as their safety concern,
and then go into steer the model.
Otherwise, yeah.
Thank you. No problem.
Great. Any additional questions for
Violet?
I guess I have one. So I'm wondering,
curious that, what do you see are
additional opportunities or
challenges that's worth solving moving
forward? I see.
Yeah. Like I said, I I still think,
like, safety, like,
hallucination, and basically
whatever all the topics that this workshop
is trying to solve are are lingering
challenges that we need to do.
And then the MOE work that make me
particularly excited
about is, for example, we identify
a handful of safety
related experts. But
I almost think that shouldn't be the behavior
of the model. If you think about it
because we know MOE
that you will have the routing
behavior, the mechanism built in, and
that will be more vulnerable So
I think the ideal behavior from my
perspective for MOE model is that
every expert should
bury some of these,
responsibility for safety, so then maybe this
is a good time
for the training, the companies that are training
this model to think about how to redesign
their objective function and all that so that they can train
better models so that they have more distributed
Yeah. Experts. Thank you. So
that's thanks, Violet, again for the great talk.
So now we'll have, coffee
break at 02:30 to
3PM. And then we will
have our last, keynote talk from professor
Yan Lu at PM.
Please come back to your seat. We will
be starting in two minutes.
With our keynote talk.
Okay. Hello, everyone. We will be starting
our last keynote on
talk for today. So, today,
we are very honored to have professor Yan
Liu from, USC
And,
of the Victoria B School of Engineering at
USC. She joined
USC in August 2010
and before that, she was a research
staff member in the data analytics group
at IBM Watson Center. And she received
her MS and PhD from Carnegie Mellon.
Her research interests are machine learning and
artificial intelligence, and
their applications to health care,
sustainability, and social media
analysis. Without further ado, let's welcome
Yan.
Thank you very much for staying for
the last session, for the whole
clear. I know that all of you are
probably very tired and exhausted after
so many days of,
great ideas and great
food. So, today I'm going
to talk a little bit about,
the research, trend that we have
been working on for the past, I would
say probably eight to ten years
on interpretability.
I know that with the development of all
these AI technologies,
with the OEM, that we are really
experiencing, the
boom of all these wonderful models
that we're using. Obviously, all
of them are black box models.
So, with respect to
the theme of the work where we have
the trustworthy AI, one
important aspect, to ensure safety
and many other trustworthiness
of AI models is really through interpretability.
I will say that interpretability is obviously
very important because this
will be very helpful, you know, to
build trust and safety
For example, when we have doctors,
in the future as AI doctor,
they would like to say that you have,
type two diabetes, you probably
don't want, the doctor to say, does this
because the AI model tells us so.
You want the doctor to tell you, like,
what we currently are
telling patients. This is because when we're looking
at your blood sugar level that is
really high or some other indicators
of the vital signs.
That indicating that you have type two diabetes.
So interpretability is really important
for trust and safety.
And then, Albert says, this is also related
to we
are all aware, of this
signature work that
was introducing the algorithm online,
where they gave example that we can easily
fool the machine with the dataset that we're having.
When we're looking at all these dataset
that we feed into these
slash ambush models, we never
have the capability to assess
the quality and
the right distribution of the data sets.
Because this is just so big and so
enormous that it's very difficult
the these different
aspects. So the machine can easily
fool, and we do not know, and that's where we
see all the hallucinations.
On the other side, there's also these
fires and fires, furnace issues,
and last but not the least, there's also
these regulations and policies
established for ensuring
the model that we developed
for the real applications will satisfy
these different type of safety
criterias. So,
we have been working on model interpretability
for a very long time. As I mentioned, you know,
the topics started probably
eight to ten years ago, when your
network was really a big deal,
So, what exactly model
interpretability, I think, people
have different definitions. One of
them say that, okay, basically,
this explains the degree to which
the observer can understand the causes
of a prediction. So,
when we digest, in terms
of the definition, we can that
there are a few things. One is the observer.
Right? Who are the observers
Ours' matter a lot in terms of the interpretation.
And second part is really understand
What does it mean by comprehending
the interpretations? Right? To a
scientist, probably we can understand
PD equations, To a doctor, they
are very good at understanding
the rules. And then to some
common people like, you know, our grandpas
and grandmas, they really have to
use this common sense. So from
that perspective, understanding is really
like an action very difficult
to define. And then last but not least
is also the causes of a prediction,
I know this morning, we
have the invited talk talking about, you know,
how we can actually build in causal
representations within the
model that we're building for large language
and many other and
and therefore understanding the causes
of the prediction is also important.
So, usually, there are two type of
observers that we see in the real world
applications. One type is a machine
learning researcher. Like
us that we really want to understand how
the model works, For example,
we see hallucination,
we see there's, this leakage information,
we see there's this agroscope attack that
potentially happens We really
want to understand what exactly
is, happening within the model.
And so that we will be able to do model
debugging. Another type
of user, really the end users
of these models, they don't understand
how the machine learning model actually
works in practice.
But, they are basically, you
know, decision makers
and or the users of different type of
ML products, So
from that perspective, then their understanding
terms of interpretability and
their demand of what type of interpretability
is needed also vary
differently, you know, from the machine learning
practitioners. So I
would say that interpretability is really
more like, you know, the blind touching
elephants depending on which part that we touches
in terms of this particular
elephant, then our feeling in
terms of the needs for interpretability
also varies. Over the years,
you know, many different type of model interpretations
has happened, featuring plots,
and then you see using the Shapley values,
or model representation, and then
we also see these rules and
these three traits, And then
in terms of the ways of
interpret either we can do
direct interpretation that is directly
interpreting what is happening in the
model, using feature importance
or output gradients. Or,
we can observe in terms of indirect
interpretations that is using
auxiliary models to approximate
especially locally what is happening
within respect to the complex model.
And then, there's also the global
interpretation and local interpretation. Either
explaining what is happening
with the whole complex models,
or, you know, locally that particular
prompt that we're interested in
what happens and why we come out with the answers
with this particular prompt.
So what does interpretability brings us? Right?
It really give us a lot of
understanding in terms of what
is happening But on the other side,
I would say that interpretability
is really inherently means an information
loss. So, even though there have
been many many interpretability
models or algorithms have been developed
there's this this major gap
One, as I mentioned, is really the interpretability.
Versus the information loss. We
interpret the complex model,
which with feature is really
important, And this is really
a very rough
approximation in terms of what actually happens
within the CNN models or
within the LSTM models.
The other side is that when
we have the interpretability, when
I work with many of the domain experts,
they really appreciate that. But
after they see interpretability,
there's actually no downstream applications.
In terms of what exactly we can do in
there. Last but not the
least, we all know that interpretability is
connected with the rest of fairness
and robustness and safety.
But there has not been a rigorous way
to define how interpretability
will be able to connect it with all these
important safety and ethical
questions that we're interested. So I would
say that from that perspective, there
obviously has been a lot of wonderful work
but there's also these major gaps.
So one of the things that we try to solve
this gap is,
trying to see if we can actually characterize
these interpretability
with more accurate terms.
So one of the accurate terms that we look
around and we found very interesting
is so called the speech interaction.
So, first, just a quick
introduction for future interaction.
In regression problem. We have input features,
from x one, x two, and x three.
And then we want to know what will
be the predictors for y.
Typically, we will represent them, you
know, as a function over x
and y, between x and
to y. And then the in terms
of the function form, we say there is this
linear form. This is typically called as
the main effects. And then there is this
higher order interaction effects.
Where these will be basically capturing a lot
of these complex relationships between
the features, and that is really
difficult, for human to discern.
So, we care about these feature interact
because, as I mentioned, we want to have better
accurate interpretability, and,
obviously, modeling these interactions
accurately will also improving these
model accuracies.
They also can help us explain these
predictions especially
for researchers and domain
scientific domain, then
they will be able to capture these
hair odor interactions especially
in the scientific equations or PDE
formulas, right, these are the
ones that domain experts and,
will not be able to really
good at capturing and they will
really want to rely on the AI models
to do so. And then
the last part is our
very important, as I mentioned, in terms of actionable
interpretability is that after
the interpretation, we really want
to build a more interpretable
model with similar prediction performance,
as complex models that we use right
now. So this really serves
as the purposes of model compression
and also model robust
And, so one of the things we started
with with the future interaction because
we don't know the form of the function,
is that we're looking at the feature interaction
sets. That is, we want
to identify these
interaction sets that
will be in this non additive
groupings in the function form.
For example, here, if we know the ground
truth of f one function,
as a falling form, then we see, oh,
the first interaction sets in this f
one function is, x one,
x two, and x three. And then
the second term is just involving
one feature, x four, we don't need to worry
about And then the third term is
x three and x five. And then
similarly for the second example,
where we have f two, then
this will be more like a log
x one plus log x two. And
there's no interaction sets in here, so we
say there's interaction set is none.
So, I would say that this
particular concept obviously has
been there for a very, very long time.
This can be dated back in the
eighteen forties, where people
are looking at the different type of experiment designs.
And then later, you know, the statistics
community looking at us from the
perspective analysis of variance and linear
regression, and then machine
learning community looking at those from tree
based methods, a part or
mixed partial derivatives,
and etcetera. We have a long history.
We know this is a really important aspect
it's just that we have gone through a long
wave for large language models
and neural network
We sometimes may not necessarily think of this
as something that is powerful and useful
as it was when the model was relatively
simple. So,
our journey for interpretability
through the lenses of future interaction
started, as I mentioned, in
2018.
The speech student, Michael Zhang, his
whole thesis work centers around this.
Where he basically introduced this neural
interaction detector
where, we introduced this,
particular interaction
set identification by examining
the weights of the GPU network.
And then afterwards, we were able to
build an efficient model
to identify all the interaction sets
any order, of interaction sets
through these greedy based methods.
And last but not least, we're also able
to do model reduction
through this generalized additive model,
utilizing the interaction sets
we identified. So,
we think that interaction
set is important because we can
think of neural network in
general as actually a universal
function approximator. That
means that you were able to accurately
identify any type of higher order interactions
that is underlying
in the data distribution. And then
the optimization algorithm is obviously
trying to identify and reducing
all the unnecessary interaction
sets And that's how they will be able to come
up with really complex functions
that fits the data really, really well.
So, and, we basically
said that now we're looking at
the future interaction set for
any particular of neural network
Our journey started, with a so
called feed forward neural network.
So, let's say we consider, this
neural network with L
and then p l will be the number of
hidden units. In
the l's layer. So input
feature will be the zeros layer,
and then, p zero will obviously be
p, that is the number of input features,
We were representing the weight matrices
using w, and
w l will representing
the weight matrices in the LST layer,
and then, we have phi,
which is actually the
And and this is the formulation
for the feed forward neural network.
So, after we define the
neural network terminology,
the key concepts that we introduced here
is that we noticed that
for any input features,
that is a raw feature, right,
if they interacting with each other,
obviously, there must be one particular
common hidden unit. Where,
the input features, will follow
strongly weight connections. So
for example, here we say that in the
original function of f x,
they learn through the neural network,
If there is a term that is
have an interaction set of x
one and x three, then there
must be a particular
hidden unit For example, here we say
this is a hidden unit in the
first layer, where base
captures the the future
interactions between x one and x three.
That means their weights, their corresponding
weights from x one to this
hidden units, and x three to this hidden units
is really high. So based
on this particular type of
observations, we were able to
identify a particular algorithm
so that we can quickly identify all
the feature interaction sets.
In the learned neural network
architecture. And then
we have this particular dilemma
to say that, oh, what the observations,
is actually true. And
specifically, this common hidden
units usually happen within the
first hidden layer. And that is why in
a lot of the computer
vision application, where you do see
that in the first hidden layer, you started
to see eyes and
also the mouth, when we try to identify
a face of a human. And etcetera.
Later, we have work to say that if this
heat interaction happens in higher layer,
we'll still be able to have an algorithm
to develop that.
So, really quickly for the idea of
the neural interaction detector
the proposed algorithm is as follows. That
is we first train this
feed forward neural network with the
sparse weights, using the regularization.
And then we're going to rank all the
weights, by interpreting them
and then hopefully, we'll be able to have a
cutoff in terms of the ranking
of different interaction sets.
So, this is the theoretical results
to say that if we go through this way,
we'll be able to provide this
upper bound, to approximate
on how
these latent variables will be
contributing to the final outputs.
So, next, a quick definition
in terms of how we define
the interaction weights for any sets
of interaction sets we want to evaluate.
So here, let's say that we have
the l's layer of hidden units, and then
I is interaction says we are in
evaluating on.
They consist of two parts. The
first part is z I one
and this part is, you're representing
basically how important that particular
hidden units to the final output.
And this can be approximated by
the weight matrices taking
absolute value all the way to the,
the top layer. And then the
second component is really
evaluating in terms of how each element
in this interaction set how
each feature in this interaction set
contributing to the impact
for that particular hidden unit.
And obviously, because it's of a because
it's a set, we have to
have a way to aggregate all the features
in the sets. The way
that we evaluate is taking the minimum
value of the weights. There
are two reasons for that. One of
them is because using the minimum
value where we'll be able to
define this w,
I as really a submodular function,
where we will be able to use the
greedy based algorithms to get a
very scalable algorithm. And the second
one is that we
basically, that proof
under certain assumptions, this
minimum value will capture the strength
of the interaction sets really nicely.
So, yeah, this is basically, the
proof, for the
ranking of the higher order interactions
using a greedy based approach.
Because of the minimum value and sub modular
capacity, we are able to prove
that using the Grady based
algorithm search, we will
be able to get
the global optimal interaction
sets weights. So,
after this particular algorithm was
introduced, later we
were able to grow this
into explaining any type of
neural networks. For example, as I mentioned,
we started with a feed forward neural net
work with a very specific
model, through the
global interpretation, and to later
expand this to the model
which can explain any type of neural
network. And then later,
that we're also able to not only be able
to identify the
interaction set, but also the
attribution that is how important
this interaction set
in the model, whole model for
inside the neural net
So, this is what Michael has done, and
obviously, he completed his thesis.
Some of the algorithm were able to deploy
it within the meta,
advertisement ranking system.
And then later that, we started
a new era after PhD student,
James, joined. We started
to look more into specific
aspect in terms of how we can do actionable
interpretability. So
one of the threat, he does is that we
want to see how we will be able to build
a white box models. Utilizing
the interaction set that we
identified. And we developed the sign
model, which we called as a sparse
interaction additive networks. So that we'll
be able to achieve similar performance as
a neural network. I'll show and
also a little bit more detail, afterwards.
And then we also talk a little bit
how we connect interpretability
with fairness for the health care application.
In this EM NLP paper,
we work with the Google
cloud AI researchers, to
explain how we can
utilize the INTERSHAP
algorithm
so that we can explain how the
answers from the
or other type of large
language models, which particular sentence
or which particular article the
answer is actually coming from.
Last but not the least,
we also work more through interpretability
for model debugging. Because
after we get the different type of interpretive,
interpretabilities, we
really want to see how we will be able to
the results
and the model further so that we can
get better results, especially
this is making a lot of sense in
applications, for example, in healthcare,
where there's a limited amount of data.
Where basically that we're able to build a
model that we're able to
predict, you know, cancers,
or other type of disease, but the
performance is not as good
for other type of tasks.
And utilizing this
model debugging, through the
interpretability and getting the domain
knowledge from the domain experts
we were able to get better results using
the student teacher model.
For model debugging. So
next, I'm going to talk quickly,
for the first work
one of them, is,
sign work, as I mentioned. This is
really, work where we try to build
a model that is interpretable, but also
we're able to achieve very similar
prediction performance as our original neural network.
So the way it works, is as follows.
So we build, this deep neural
network, as I mentioned, and then we
try to interpret and identify
the interaction sets this can be just,
individual feature or pairwise,
or even higher order. And we were
given the ranking of them. And
then later, we're going to build the so
called generalized additive model,
where we're going to select the highest
ranked interaction sets, and
putting them into the generalized additive
model.
So in this particular step, we won't
know the function form. The way
we do this is through
building a simple, feature
feed forward neural network to approximating
the function form. So once we added
one feature interaction set, we see how
the performance goes. Comparing with
the deep neural network. That
we trained. If, it's not as good,
then what we're going to do is selecting
the second highest
interaction sets and then adding them into
the generalized additive model.
And we go through this iterative step
using these global,
sorry, using these local optimal
selection processes.
We are able to finally
getting this final generalized
additive model. That, will
achieve very similar performance as the
neural network. And now when we're
looking at the neural net the generalized additive
model, it is
significantly more interpretable than our original
neural network, because now
we see what type of interaction sets
in there, and what are important in the
generalized adaptive model.
This gives us a much better and
much robust, result
models in the end. So
quickly, I want to show the experiment
results we conduct experiment
results on a few UCI data
sets and also
the Mimic three data sets.
Here that, we show that comparing
with different models, and
also the neural network model,
we were able to achieve
similar prediction performance
on several tasks, and sometimes it can be
even better. And
this also happens similarly for
the Mimic
three datasets, with respect
to the AU ROC evaluation.
So, the next, work that I want
to talk quickly is really the evaluation
of this different type of
interpretable methods. We know that,
examining the future importance is really
important, that's a lot of the interpretability matters
works. But we
have not conducted a rigorous
evaluation of different,
interpretability methods.
There's not a very good, standard
on how to do it, So at that
time that we explore different options,
it seems that, this raw method
that is removing
remove and, retrain model,
is one typical approach
people will do when we do not the
ground truth of the future importance.
So, this is what we did,
on this, mimic four
datasets. We're looking at the
prediction of the
mortality for different
patients across different age groups.
And in there, that, for different
methods, for example,
for transformer, or
this attention
based, LSCM methods,
we can interpret using all
the state of art interpretability methods
at time. For example, we can
have the sharps,
sharply sampling, model,
gradient shop, and etcetera.
And then our methods, which is
based on the neural interaction
detector, as I mentioned, which is
called ARC Detect. We were able
to achieve the most
significant performance
decrease once we remove all these
features. So that means that
the model were really able to identify
more robust
most important features.
Comparing with other interpretability methods.
And then, yeah, this
is something similar that, again,
we are able to get the best performance,
in identifying the future
importance. And then in
the paper, I didn't have the time
to looking at the specific
discuss the specific results connecting with
the fairness. We're also
examining how fairness will be connected
with interpretability results
In there, we demonstrate and also with
specific examples
to demonstrate that in
this healthcare data set, we
identify that a lot of these,
mortality rates are really high
associated with people that is
in the underrepresentative groups.
So this is a very important way
to examining the fairness,
if we're looking at the real world datasets.
So, with that,
I would say that
I'm using this quick twenty
something minutes, I gave a quick overview
in terms of how we will be able to
utilizing this feature
interaction lenses to build
an interpretability methods and then with the
downstreaming actions that we can have.
I would say that interpretations are really
important, The
the interesting part is that there's
no right or wrong answers. But
there are obviously some useful ones that we can
use, and that's why we want to
address the actionable interpretability.
And then feature interaction, we think that
it provides a really unique
for the interpretations And most
importantly, we think this provide the minimum
information loss between
the interpretation
and, the the neural network, the
original neural network that we built.
So I think with that,
I would say that actionable interpretability
is really the future we really
hope there will be more conversations
around this topic. And
then, we'll be very happy
to start collaborations if you're interested
to explore this through the lenses of
future interaction. Yeah. Thank you.
Okay. Thanks, Yan, for the excellent talk. Any
questions from the audience?
Yes.
I have some questions related
to the explanation model.
Uh-huh. Because you consider the interactions
So if, let's say, if, like, I have a lot
of variables, how do you
consider you know, the different
different number of combinations
like up to maybe 100, 1,000,
That's a really good question. So I would say,
that for the
model that we built through the neural network,
we have many local optimals. That
means that there are different ways that you can combine
these feature interaction sets.
So the way that we do this is really just simply
interpreting which interaction
says that this particular model learned.
Obviously, that, you have the same architectures,
but you have different c's or different initial
starting points, different optimization. You'll
get a different model. And then
you actually will lead to a different
interaction sets in there. Yeah. But
what we do is really faithful explaining
the interaction sets that identified by
that particular model.
Yes. Another
question is, like, in the evaluation, like,
in the scenario, we don't know the ground truth.
Right? And how do we effectively evaluate
or models? Yeah.
So, I mentioned this a little bit in the
talk where one of the methods
to say that we can do remove and retrain.
Basically, we identify the most important
features and we remove them
and then retrain the model to see how
the performance decrease. If
it decrease significantly, that means, oh,
this is really the most important feature.
I wouldn't say this is the best way. It's
just the one way people design it. But
I would really say the most important way
to evaluate the interpretability
is really through these
downstreaming, ways. For example,
whether you can actually rebuild an
interpretable model afterwards.
Thank you.
Okay. Great. Any additional questions?
For Yan?
Yes.
So I have a more
higher level question in terms of
feature interaction is what you are looking at here.
While spaCyte encoders and other model.
New model. That are trying to
decompose the features. Mhmm.
Is there a philosophical understanding, or
are they both at two different ends of
the spectrum? Yeah. That's a really good question.
I think this, connecting
in terms of how
we understanding, you know, the features that
the representations we learned
which is really the essence
for neural network. Think that's
the way that it does, right, is when you're
looking at the behaviors,
a lot of them, for example,
token in large language model or
video images in
the image pixels. Right? They
started with these raw features, tokens
or, pixels. And then they
build on top of it. So I would say that these
type of applications is really more in
terms of how we composing
the different, lower
level features to higher level. Right? And then
they will be able to build a
model. So that is why the model I
I will say the interpretability for these
type of matters these type of
models are really making sense. In
many scientific domains where that
actually get some observations,
it's just a human we see can measure.
Right? Or, for example, in health care
application where we see the vital signs.
And from that perspective, then a
lot of the are really learning the latent
representation terms of what is happening
beneath the vital signs that we can measure,
or beneath scientific metrics we
can measure. Then
that there is a small, late
representations that we have to learn,
but it won't be reflected into
the model. In terms of final prediction.
And that is why, you know, that we see in terms
of the form, it is still just a combination
of the features. So,
yeah, I I I would love
to follow-up on this to see if, there's any
better way to underlying
or uncovering
the underlying features. Right?
This can be higher
that might be to higher dimensions. Right? And
then dissecting them more,
than composing the features,
leading to a higher level representation.
Thank you. Great.
Okay. That's thanks Yen again for the excellent
talk.
So for people at the poster, can you
come back to the seat first?
We will have our next session.
Okay. So our next section
is our poster session two.
And networking. But before that, because
the slides live needs to stop
the recording, so we
need to do the closing remark first.
Okay. So,
so this workshop is about trustworthy
AI, and we have, eight organizers here.
And thanks everyone for coming to the
workshop and also poster,
presentations.
And we also have the next trustworthy
ad workshop at the CBPR.
So this is called the Truvy
workshop and this is on Thursday, June
fourth, at Denver USA.
If you're interested, in attending, this is our workshop,
website, and, we would love
to see you there at Denver.
Okay. So then let's go back
to our poster session two and networking.
So then we will stop at 04:30.
So if you're, at 04:30,
please take your poster off.
And now is the time for the poster session
networking. Okay. Thanks, everyone.